<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">the part of AHA! that processes
adaptation rules, updates user profiles, and adapts content</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="long" type="creole">The engine is the part of AHA! that processes
adaptation rules, updates user profiles and adapts content. For every type of content,
AHA! can use a different 'handler' to adapt it to the user's needs. Updating user profiles
is done by queuing the adaptation rules that are part of concept's //access//
attribute.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">The engine of AHA! is driven by web clients (mostly
users with a browser) that request a page or concept of AHA!. Initially AHA! only
supported requests for pages, an idea taken from [[../research/early-aha|earlier
versions]]. A request in the form of a URL would look like this:

{{{ http://aha.win.tue.nl:18080/aha/Get/coursename/page.html }}}

The 'Get' servlet will ask the {{{HandlerManager}}} to locate the resource
{{{'coursename/page.html'}}}. As this is a local resource the location will be on the AHA!
server. Next, the {{{ProfileManager}}} is told that the specific resource is accessed. It
will attempt to find a matching concept and associated adaptation rules. This starts the
user profile update. Finally, the {{{HandlerManager}}} is invoked to call the various
content handlers installed to adapt the specific resource type.

In a later version requests for a concept instead of a page were allowed in AHA!. A
request would look like this:

{{{ http://aha.win.tue.nl:18080/aha/Get/coursename/?concept=coursename.concept }}}

The 'Get' servlet will look up the appropriate page through information stored in the
DM/AM. This option later allowed multiple pages per concept, where the actual page shown
depends on the UM. In [[../gale|GALE]] many to many relations are allowed between concept
and resource. A resource can no longer be used to uniquely identify a concept. Hence,
accessing information through a page URL as was possible in AHA! is no longer allowed in
GALE.

=== Profile Update ===

When a page is accessed, the {{{ProfileManager}}} will be informed to update the user
profile. The matching concept data is loaded and adaptation rules stored in the
{{{access}}} attribute are loaded in a queue. The rules are then executed one by one. If a
rule updates another attribute value and the rule allowed triggering, the other
attribute's adaptation rules are loaded and placed at the end of the queue. The process
continues until the queue is empty.

Initially the [[=http://www.singularsys.com/jep/|JEP]] parser was used to evaluate
expressions (it was open source at the time). At a later time a new parser was written
that was more flexible, e.g. allowing variable lookup on the fly instead of providing a
symbol table up front. The parser allowed basic arithmetic functions with the UM as
variables.

=== 'Handling' a Resource ===

Content handlers are registered with the {{{HandlerManager}}}. In the initial version of
AHA! there were different handlers for HTML, XML and XHTML. The {{{HTMLHandler}}} used the
[[=http://docs.oracle.com/javase/1.4.2/docs/api/javax/swing/text/html/HTMLEditorKit.html|Java
Swing HTML toolkit]] to parse HTML files, supporting HTML 3.2. The other two handlers
relied on the [[=http://xerces.apache.org/xerces-j/|Xerces]] XML parser. They interpret
[[authoring-content|instructions]] in the HTML, XML and XHTML content like &lt;if>,
&lt;object> and conditional &lt;a> tags.

The three handlers contained some similarities, because conditional constructs like
&lt;if> tags could occur in all three formats. A later version of AHA! changed the
structure so that handlers could process each others output. This allowed a simpler
{{{HTMLHandler}}} that converted the HTML to XHTML. The {{{XMLHandler}}} would handle the
&lt;if> tags, and the {{{XHTMLHandler}}} would only handle (X)HTML specific tags like the
anchor (&lt;a>) tag.

In [[../gale|GALE]] the idea of a [[../gale/system/adaptation-engine|modular approach]] to
[[../gale/system/processors|processing a resource]] is extended.</gale:text>

</gale:repo>