<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">a Java-based authoring tool that allows
the creation of high level DM/AM models using a GUI to draw a graph of concepts and
relations</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="long" type="creole">The Graph Author was developed by Brendan
Rousseau, a student at the TU/e. It is a high level DM/AM authoring tool that allows most
authors to create their adaptive application without ever writing any AHA! rules, as seen
in the [[concept-editor|concept editor]]. The tool generates these
rules based on [[templates|template code]] associated with relations.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">The Graph Author was developed by Brendan Rousseau,
a student at the TU/e. It is a high level DM/AM authoring tool that allows most authors to
create their adaptive application without ever writing any AHA! rules, as seen in the
[[concept-editor|concept editor]]. The tool generates these rules based on
[[templates|template code]] associated with relations. Relations are drawn on the main
screen between concepts. Relations also exist in the form of a concept hierarchy displayed
on the left.

{{images/graphauthor.gif|The main screen of the graph author}}

The templates for concepts may specify user model updates that depend on the hierarchy. In
a museum site a visit to a lower-level concept may indicate interest in the parent
concept, and in a course such a visit may 'generate' knowledge of the parent concept.
Concepts are dragged to the graph pane where they can be connected in any arbitrary way by
concept relationships. The figure above shows a number of prerequisite relationships that
cause link adaptation by checking the 'suitability' attribute of concepts. There are also
some 'visibility' relationships that influence the presentation style for different
fragments of text. The existence of adaptation rules is mostly invisible to authors using
the Graph Author. Only in the adaptive resource selection for the conditional inclusion of
objects and the adaptive link destinations do expressions over user model attributes
become visible.</gale:text>

</gale:repo>