<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">writing instructions in the content of a
hypermedia resource to help adapt to the user's needs</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="long" type="creole"></gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">As seen in [[../research/early-aha|earlier
versions]] of AHA!, an author may want to influence the adaptation of content directly
using 'if' statements. The expression used in the 'if' statement should be able to refer
to the user model. Since HTML, XML and XHTML are the content types AHA! supports by
default, the 'if' statements are created using tags:

{{{
&lt;if expr="de_koninck.interest &gt; 70">&lt;block>
    As you have seen in the topic about De Koninck,
    there is really no better beer.
&lt;/block>&lt;block>
    To find out everything about the best beer around,
    read the topic about De Koninck.
&lt;/block>&lt;/if>
}}}

AHA! (actually one of the '[[engine|content handlers]]') will evaluate the expression
using the current user's profile. Depending on the outcome, either the first or the second
block will be chosen. Only that block of text will appear in the result that is send to
the user.

Link adaptation is another [[../research/taxonomy|technique]] that AHA! uses to adapt
(X)HTML content. An author can indicate that a link should be adapted by the adaptation
engine by making the 'class' attribute 'conditional':

{{{
&lt;a href="de_koninck" class="conditional">
}}}

This will make AHA! lookup the referenced concept and the CSS class of the link will be
changed depending on the user model. By default AHA! uses the {{{suitability}}} and
{{{visited}}} attributes to determine the class:
* a link to a concept for which {{{suitability}}} is {{{false}}}, will be black
* a link to a concept for which {{{suitability}}} is {{{true}}} and {{{visited}}}
  {{{false}}}, will be blue
* a link to a concept for which {{{suitability}}} is {{{true}}} and {{{visited}}}
  {{{true}}}, will be purple

A later addition to AHA! was conditional object inclusion. A concept definition can
include a 'casegroup'. The casegroup defines several resources that are linked to one
concept. Depending on the user model (using an expression), one of the resources is
selected when the concept is requested. This can be used when creating so-called
'fragment' concepts. The resources for these concepts typically contain some fragment
(X)HTML. The fragment can be included inside another resource:

{{{
&lt;object name="beer_description" type="aha/text" />
}}}

When the concept is accessed, an adaptation rule is triggered that will update the user
model. Depending on the user model, one of the resources defined in the casegroup of the
'beer_description' concept will be included. This process can be used to show a
comprehensive explanation on beer the first time the object is included. The second a
compact explanation is used, etc.</gale:text>

</gale:repo>