<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">describing the various ways to use
[[../gam|GAM]] to define [[../domain-model|domain]] and [[../adaptation-model|adaptation
model]].</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="long" type="creole"><gale:object name="../gam?tags=long" />

GAM files can be used inside HTML, in concepts.gam files stored with
the content, in authoring tools, stored on the GALE server, etc.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">The definitions stored in the [[../gam|GAM]] format
should somehow be made available to the [[../system/adaptation-engine|]], the part of the
GALE [[../system|system]] that actually serves content to clients. The following options
are available:
* [[external-tools|External tools]] embed GAM code in their formats. When an application
  or course is deployed to GALE, either the original format is presented to GALE or,
  preferably, the tool creates a GAM file that is presented to GALE.
* A GAM file can be deployed to GALE through a special interface. GALE will interpret the
  file and store the concepts defined in it in the database.
* A GAM file can be stored in the $GALE_HOME/config directory on the GALE server, making
  the concepts defined in it available upon restarting GALE.
* GAM files can be [[bundled]] with the actual content. This will allow GALE to discover
  the GAM file based on the URI of the concept requested. As the author does not need to
  know about the GALE server at all, this option requires the least administration. If the
  content and GAM files are stored on the internet, the application is instantly available
  to all GALE servers that trust the domain of the content server.
* GAM can be stored inside the HTML files using a &lt;meta> tag. This brings back some of
  the ideas in [[../../research/early-aha|early AHA! versions]] and Interbook
  [[../../references?tags=Brus98|[Brus98~]]], where content and domain/adaptation model
  were written in the same file.
</gale:text>

</gale:repo>