<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">future work that would improve upon the
current state-of-the-art adapative hypermedia systems</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;long" type="creole"></gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">To further improve performance, more of the work
that GALE has to do needs to be distributed. One option would be to allow the creation of
a GALE server pool, where work is evenly distributed over servers in the pool. Another
option is to do some or most of the work on the client. This option would allow better
scaling (since the processing power increases with the number of active clients). GALE's
architecture already loosely couples several components using an
[[gale/system/events|event bus]]. The [[gale/system/adaptation-engine|adaptation engine]]
might be modified to allow it to run inside the client's browser. This would greatly
reduce GALE's workload. Furthermore, it allows changes to the content after the page is
shown. Some user model values might be stored elsewhere on the internet or require
advanced reasoning to deduce. When the adaptation engine in the client receives these user
model values, the page can be updated on the fly. This would allow a very fast initial
response.

The reasoning behind adaptation is not visible to the reader. When links are recommended
or not, and when blocks of text appear or are removed, the reader may want to know why.
Scrutability by the reader may lead to improved learning. Scrutability exists for user
model information [[references?tags=Kay02|[Kay02~]]] but a lot of UM data in GALE is
intended to steer the adaptation and is not meaningful for the end-user, so scrutability
of the UM data requires more than just giving access to the data. Scrutability of the
adaptation has not been studied in general at all. There is a limited form of adaptation
scrutability in Interbook by means of the "teach me" functionality. Similar functionality
can be found in this thesis through the prerequisite boxes that are also available when a
concept is unsuitable. But how do we extend GALE to help readers find this type of
information without the author explicitely defining it (as is done in this thesis)?

When GALE is used in a Technology-Enhanced Learning setting, there is no feedback on how
'good' the adaptation is. A human teacher will learn from mistakes in the learning path he
chose when presenting the material. Data mining on extended GALE logs could be used to
automatically find problems in the suggested learning paths and alter the adaptation
accordingly. GALE currently does not log whether a concept access was through a
recommended link or not. It is computationally hard to recompute this after the fact. So
GALE needs to log more in order to facilitate data mining on its log data.

Searching in adaptive hypermedia is more difficult than in traditional hypertext. As the
text can be different from one user to another, the search results should also be
different. For a particular user, traditional indexing methods might return results that
do not include the term searched for. A new GALE [[gale/system/processors|processor]]
might index pages after they are fully adapted. A probabilistic model can be used to
indicate the chance that a specific term is found in a concept. This would allow searching
and ordering of adaptive material in an efficient manner.

Because GALE requires a login, the material is not accessible to search engines, severely
limiting the chances of being found. A special [[gale/system/extending-login|Login
Handler]] could be developed that detects the search engine's bot that crawls the Web.
When the search engine views the material, adaptation would be turned off and all the
material would be shown.

Being able to distribute the resources that make up an adaptive application on the World
Wide Web, could be called Open Corpus. However, true 'Open Corpus Adaptation' would be
able to adapt information that was not authored with adaptation in mind. GALE could
perform a shallow analysis of the material and detect whether the material might have some
relevance to a concept. The adaptation rules attached to the concept might be used to
adapt the new information, for instance helping to determine if the material is suitable
or not.</gale:text>

</gale:repo>