<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text type="creole" expr="gale.req().getParameter(&quot;tags&quot;) != null"> You can
see all references <gale:a href="references" adapt="false"
class="good">here</gale:a>.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Abel09" type="creole">[Abel09]

Abel, F., Heckmann, D., Herder, E., Hidders, J., Houben, G.J., Krause, D., Leonardi, E.,
van der Sluijs, K.: A framework for flexible user profile mashups, Int. Workshop on
Adaptation and Personalization for Web 2.0 at UMAP '09, CEUR Workshop Proceedings,
2009.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Akker06" type="creole">[Akker06]

Akkermans, P., Aroyo, L., Bellekens, P., iFanzy: Personalised Filtering Using Semantically
Enriched TV-Anytime Content. Demo at the Third European Semantic Web Conference,
2006.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Amen04" type="creole">[Amen04]

Amendola, I., Cena, F., Console, L. Crevola, A., Goy, A., Modeo, S., Perrero, M., Torre,
I., Toso, A., UbiquiTO: a Multi-Device Adaptive Guide. Proceedings of the sixth
International Symposium on Mobile Human-Computer Interaction – MobileHCI, pp. 13-16,
Springer Verlag, 2004.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Bloch08" type="creole">[Bloch08]

Bloch, J., Effective Java, Second Edition, Prentice Hall Press, 2008.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Brus96" type="creole">[Brus96]

Brusilovsky, P., Schwarz, E.W., Weber, G., ELM-ART: An Intelligent Tutoring System on
World Wide Web. Proceedings of ITS’96, the Third International Conference on Intelligent
Tutoring Systems, Springer LNCS 1086, pp. 261-269, 1996.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Brus96-2" type="creole">[Brus96-2]

Brusilovsky, P., Methods and techniques of adaptive hypermedia, User Modeling and
User-Adapted Interaction 6(2-3), pp. 87-129, 1996.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Brus98" type="creole">[Brus98]

Brusilovsky, P., Eklund, J., Schwarz, E., Web-based education for all: A tool for
developing adaptive courseware. Computer Networks and ISDN Systems (Proceedings of the 7th
Int. World Wide Web Conference, 30 (1-7), pp. 291-300, 1998.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Brus01" type="creole">[Brus01]

Brusilovsky, P., Adaptive hypermedia, User Modeling and User-Adapted Interaction 11(1-2),
pp. 87-110, 2001.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Brus03" type="creole">[Brus03]

Brusilovsky, P., Santic, T., De Bra, P., A Flexible Layout Model for a Web-Based Adaptive
Hypermedia Architecture, Proceedings of the AH2003 Workshop, TU/e CSN 03/04, pp. 77-86,
Budapest, Hungary, May 2003.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Bush45" type="creole">[Bush45]

Bush, V., As We May Think!, Atlantic Monthly, Vol. 176 No. 1, pp. 101-108,
1945.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Calvi97" type="creole">[Calvi97]

Calvi, L., De Bra, P., Using Dynamic Hypertext to create Multi-Purpose Textbooks,
Proceedings of ED-MEDIA’97, 1997.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Conlan04" type="creole">[Conlan04]

Conlan, O., Wade, V., Evaluation of APeLS – An Adaptive eLearning Service Based on the
Multi-model, Metadata-Driven Approach, Proceedings of the third International Conference
on Adaptive Hypermedia, Springer LNCS 3137, pp. 291-295, 2004.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Cris05" type="creole">[Cris05]

Cristea, A. I., Smits, D., De Bra., P., Writing MOT, Reading AHA! - Converting Between an
Authoring and a Delivery System for Adaptive Educational Hypermedia, In Proc. of A3EH
Workshop at the AIED 2005 conference, Amsterdam, The Netherlands, pages 107-114,
2005.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;DeBra96" type="creole">[DeBra96]

De Bra, P. M. E., Teaching Hypertext and Hypermedia through the Web, Journal of Universal
Computer Science 2(12), pp. 797-804, 1996.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;DeBra97" type="creole">[DeBra97]

De Bra, P., Calvi, L., Creating adaptive hyperdocuments for and on the Web, Proceedings of
WebNet’97 Conference, Toronto, pp. 149–155, 1997.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;DeBra00" type="creole">[DeBra00]

De Bra, P., Aerts, A., Houben, G.J., Wu, H., Making General-Purpose Adaptive Hypermedia
Work, Proceedings of the AACE Webnet 2000 Conference, pp. 117-123, 2000.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;DeBra02" type="creole">[DeBra02]

De Bra, P., Aerts, A., Smits, D., Stash, N., AHA! Version 2.0: More Adaptation Flexibility
for Authors, In: Driscoll, M., Reeves, T.C. (eds.) Proc. of World Conference on ELearning,
E-Learn 2002, AACE, pp. 240-246, 2002.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;DeBra02-2" type="creole">[DeBra02-2]

De Bra, P., Aerts, A., Smits, D., Stash, N., AHA! meets AHAM, Second International
Conference on Adaptive Hypermedia and Adaptive Web-Based Systems, Springer LNCS 2347, pp.
381-384, 2002.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;DeBra02-3" type="creole">[DeBra02-3]

De Bra, P., Aerts, A., Rousseau, B., Concept Relationship Types for AHA! 2.0. Proceedings
of the AACE ELearn'2002 conference, October 2002, pp. 1386-1389, 2002.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;DeBra03" type="creole">[DeBra03]

De Bra, P., Aerts, A., Berden, B., De Lange, B., Rousseau, B., Santic, T., Smits, D.,
Stash, N., AHA! The Adaptive Hypermedia Architecture, Proceedings of the fourteenth ACM
Hypertext Conference, pp. 81-84, ACM Press, 2003.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;DeBra03-2" type="creole">[DeBra03-2]

De Bra, P., Santic, T., Brusilovsky, P., AHA! meets Interbook and more…, Proceedings of
the AACE ELearn 2003 Conference, pp. 57-64, 2003.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;DeBra03-3" type="creole">[DeBra03-3]

De Bra, P., Aerts, A., Berden, B., De Lange, B., Escape from the Tyranny of the Textbook:
Adaptive Object Inclusion in AHA!. Proceedings of the AACE ELearn 2003 Conference,
Phoenix, Arizona, November 2003, pp. 65-71, 2003.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;DeBra06" type="creole">[DeBra06]

De Bra, P., Smits, D., Stash, N., The Design of AHA!, Proceedings of the seventeenth ACM
Conference on Hypertext and Hypermedia, pp. 133-134, ACM Press, 2006, with adaptive
version at
[[=http://aha.win.tue.nl/ahadesign/|http://aha.win.tue.nl/ahadesign/]].</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;DeBra10" type="creole">[DeBra10]

De Bra, P., Smits, D., van der Sluijs, K., Cristea, A., Hendrix, M., GRAPPLE,
Personalization and Adaptation in Learning Management Systems, In ED-MEDIA, World
Conference on Educational Multimedia, Hypermedia &amp; Telecommunication,
2010.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;DeBra12" type="creole">[DeBra12]

De Bra, P., Smits, D., van der Sluijs, K., Cristea, A.I., Foss, J., Glahn, C., Steiner,
C., GRAPPLE: Learning Management Systems meet Adaptive Learning Environments, chapter 6
In: Intelligent and Adaptive Educational-Learning Systems: Achievements and Trends, Smart
Innovation, Systems and Technologies, KES-Springer Verlang Book Series, 2012 (to
appear).</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Hage10" type="creole">[Hage10]

Hage, W.R. van, Stash, N., Wang, Y., Aroyo, L.M., Finding your way through the Rijksmuseum
with an adaptive mobile museum guide. Proceedings of the seventh Extended Semantic Web
Conference (ESWC), pp. 46-59, 2010.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Hend08" type="creole">[Hend08]

Hendrix, M., De Bra, P., Pechenizkiy, M., Smits, D., Cristea, A. I.,·Defining adaptation
in a generic multi layer model: CAM: The GRAPPLE Conceptual Adaptation Model, Proceedings
of the 3rd European Conference on Technology-Enhanced Learning 2008, pp. 132-143, Springer
LNCS, Maastricht, The Netherlands, 2008.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Henze00" type="creole">[Henze00]

Henze, N., Adaptive hyperbooks: Adaptation for project-based learning resources. PhD
Dissertation, University of Hannover, 2000.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Houben08" type="creole">[Houben08]

Houben, G.J., van der Sluijs, K., Barna, P., Broekstra, J., Casteleyn, S., Fiala, Z.,
Frasincar, F., Hera. in: Web Engineering: Modeling and Implementing Web Applications,
Human-Computer Interaction Series, pp. 263-301, Springer Verlag, 2008.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Kay02" type="creole">[Kay02]

Kay, J., Kummerfeld, B., Lauder, P., Personis: A server for user modeling, In: De Bra, P.,
Brusilovsky, P. and Conejo, R. (eds.) Proc. of Second International Conference on Adaptive
Hypermedia and Adaptive Web-Based Systems (AH'2002), Málaga, Spain, May 29-31,
2002.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Knutov09" type="creole">[Knutov09]

Knutov, E., De Bra, P., Pechenizkiy, M., 'AH 12 years later: a comprehensive survey of
adaptive hypermedia methods and techniques', New Review of Hypermedia and Multimedia,
15:1,5-38, 2009.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Kuflik11" type="creole">[Kuflik11]

Kuflik, T., Stock, O., Zancanaro, M., Gorfinke., A., Jbara, S., Kats, S., Sheidin, J.,
Kashtan, N., A Visitor’s Guide in an Active Museum: Presentations, Communications, and
Reflection. In ACM Journal on Computing and Cultural Heritage, 3(3), ACM Press,
2011.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Ramp05" type="creole">[Ramp05]

Ramp, E., De Bra, P., Brusilovsky, P., High-Level Translation of Adaptive Hypermedia
Applications, Proceedings of the ACM Hypertext Conference, Salzburg, Austria, Sept. 7-9,
2005, pp. 126-128, 2005.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Ramp05-2" type="creole">[Ramp05-2]

Ramp, E., De Bra, P., Brusilovsky, P., Authoring and Delivery of Adaptive Electronic
Textbooks made Easy, Proceedings of the AACE ELearn'2005 Conference, Vancouver, Canada,
October 25-28, 2005, pp. 142-149, 2005.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Rossi08" type="creole">[Rossi08]

Rossi, G., Schwabe, D., Modeling and Implementing Web Applications with Oohdm. Modeling
and Implementing Web Applications, Human-Computer Interaction Series, pp. 109-155,
Springer Verlag, 2008.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Smits02" type="creole">[Smits02]

Smits, D., <a href="aha/AHA - Data design and manipulation.pdf">AHA - Data design and
manipulation</a>, Report of Internship, TU/e, 2002.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Wang08" type="creole">[Wang08]

Wang, Y., Stash, N., Aroyo, L., Gorgels, P., Rutledge, L., Schreiber, G., Recommendations
Based on Semantically-enriched Museum Collections. Journal of Web Semantics: Science,
Services and Agents on the World Wide Web, 6(4), pp. 43-50, 2008.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;Wu02" type="creole">[Wu02]

Wu, H. A., Reference Architecture for Adaptive Hypermedia Applications, doctoral thesis,
Eindhoven University of Technology, The Netherlands, ISBN 90-386-0572-2, 2002.</gale:text>

</gale:repo>