<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:object data="layout.xml" />

<gale:text type="creole">To make the layout work, this thesis does not rely on the
[[../gale/layout-tables|]] or the [[../gale/layout-css|]]. We use a template page called
<a>
<gale:attr-variable name="href" expr="${../thesis}.getUri().resolve(&quot;layout.xhtml&quot;)"/>
layout.xhtml</a>. This page refers to the various [[../gale/system/view-module|views]]
like the menu. If there are prequisite concepts you don't already know, it is this file
that includes the box that shows them. (Actually a file called
<a>
<gale:attr-variable name="href" expr="${../thesis}.getUri().resolve(&quot;prereq.xml&quot;)"/>
prereq.xml</a> is included; this file is referenced in layout.xhtml.) A title for the
concept is automatically generated based on the {{{title}}} property in the domain model.
If the concept is unsuitable (when you follow a black link), the file
<a>
<gale:attr-variable name="href" expr="${../thesis}.getUri().resolve(&quot;unsuitable.xml&quot;)"/>
unsuitable.xml</a> is shown.

The {{{#resource}}} attribute is defined in the root concept of the thesis and inherited
by most concepts. It looks like this:

{{{
#resource ='~
    if (${[[=_personal]]#first-time})
        return "[[=intro.xhtml]]";
    if (${#is-object})
        return ${.}.getUriString()+".xml";
    return "[[=layout.xhtml]]";
'
}}}
</gale:text>

<gale:text type="creole" expr="${../gale/system/galecontext#known}">As you know (since you
have read [[../gale/system/galecontext|]]), the default code runs in the
[[../gale/system/um-service|]]. The {{{GaleContext}}} is not available there. But in order
to determine what resource to use for the concept, or more specifically whether we want
the layout or just the content, we need to know if the request was for an object or not.
The adaptation engine knows this, not the UM service. The (somewhat more advanced) trick
is to create a non-persistent variable and set its value in the concept's event code where
you can use the {{{GaleContext}}}. We do something like this to have it available in the
UM service:

{{{
#is-object:Boolean
event + '${#is-object} = gale.isObject();
}}}
</gale:text>

<gale:text type="creole">Hiding topics in the menu is done like this:

{{{
#hierarchy:Boolean ='(${_concept->(personal)#menu} ||
                     (${#suitability} &amp;&amp; !${#unknown}))
                     &amp;&amp; ${->(parent)#suitability}'
}}}

Making topics that are not available in the menu also unavailable in the page is done
using the [[../gale/system/link-module|#link.hide]] attribute:

{{{
#link.hide '!${#hierarchy}'
}}}
</gale:text>

</gale:repo>