<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text type="creole">One of the main reasons to use adaptation in learning material,
like this thesis, is the existence of prerequisites. Some topics are difficult to
understand if the reader did not see 'earlier' topics. In a traditional text, a reading
order follows naturally from the linear nature of the text. An author would make sure that
topics in the text appear in such an order as to satisfy all prerequisites. A hypertext
allows more navigational freedom. The adaptation in this thesis takes prerequisites into
account when recommending links. This helps in finding your way through the material
without navigating to topics that would require 'too much' prerequisite knowledge.

In this thesis, missing a prerequisite topic does not automatically make a concept
unsuitable. The idea is that as long as all prerequisite topics don't have any unsatisfied
prerequisites themselves, you might get along fine reading the concept, as long as some
summaries help you understand the basics of the prerequisites. An example of this can be
seen with the [[../introduction|]] and [[../questions|]] topics. The Introduction is a
prerequisite of the Research Questions.
<gale:if expr="${../introduction#known}"><gale:then>
It is somewhat difficult to demonstrate as you have already read the Introduction, so all
prerequisites for Research Questions are met. I can <gale:a adapt="false" class="good"
href="../howitworks" exec="${../introduction#own-knowledge} = 0d;
${../introduction#visited} = 0;">reset</gale:a> your knowledge of the Introduction (don't
worry, I won't touch your memory, this is only done in my user profile).
</gale:then><gale:else>
But as you can see, I still recommend the Research Questions topic, even though you are
missing the prerequisite. When you do visit Research Questions, a box appears that will
show a summary of the prerequisite topic, hoping that this information will be enough to
understand the Research Questions.
</gale:else></gale:if>
<gale:if expr="${../gale/gale-code#known-all} &amp;&amp; ${../gale/system/link-module#known}">
The reset function works by using an adaptive link with code that is executed when the
link is clicked:

<pre>
&lt;gale:a adapt="false" class="good" href="../howitworks"
        exec="${../introduction#own-knowledge} = 0d;
              ${../introduction#visited} = 0;">reset&lt;/gale:a>
</pre>
</gale:if>

</gale:text>

</gale:repo>