<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">presenting content in such a way that it
suits the user best</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="long" type="creole">Presenting content in a suitable way might involve
more than just showing the actual content. Different types of menus, a guide that shows
the user where to go next, or other views might contribute to the adaptivity of the
application. These views should be layed out, and their content might depend on the
[[domain-model|domain model]] and [[user-model|user model]]. Different techniques to
layout components in a browser exist and are supported by GALE, like CSS or HTML
tables.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">The presentation of a concept by GALE can be as
simple as showing the result of the [[locating-content|selected]], optionally
[[modifying-resource|modified]] resource. However, GALE supports several techniques to
layout a presentation that includes multiple views. What layout is actually used and what
content is shown in the views can be adaptive. To use layout, some specific attributes
need to be present in the concept's [[domain-model|domain model]]. Which attributes need
to be present depends on the specific technique used to create the layout. The two
techniques currently implemented are:
* Layout [[layout-css|using CSS]]
* Layout [[layout-tables|using tables]] and an &lt;iframe>

Layout is often used in combination with views, where the content is presented in one
frame (a portion of the user's screen) and other frames use generated content. This
generated content can be a menu, some additional information on the current concept,
relations to other concepts, etc. The [[system/view-module||&lt;gale:view>]] tag is often
used to generate this content. Several views exist by default:
* {{{static-tree-view}}}, a menu that displays the current concept and all parents and
  their siblings
* {{{single-list-view}}}, a menu that displays all parents, the previous and next sibling,
  and all children in a single list
* {{{next-view}}}, a link to the next suitable concept in the hierarchy
* {{{file-view}}}, displays contents of a file or an expression
</gale:text>

</gale:repo>