<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text type="creole">The menu <gale:if expr="${../_personal#menu}"><gale:then>on the left</gale:then><gale:else> at the top </gale:else></gale:if> is generated on the fly based on the current state of the user model. Some items may be
hidden based on an expression. For instance, I hide topics of which the parent topic is
not suitable. Only when the parent becomes suitable, can you see them in the menu (or
follow them through a link on a page). Hiding and showing the menu is also done through
the user model.
<gale:if expr="${../_personal#menu}"><gale:then>
If you want me to <gale:a href="../howitworks" exec="${../_personal#menu} = false;">hide
the menu</gale:a>, that is no problem.
<gale:if expr="${../gale/gale-code#known-all} &amp;&amp; ${../gale/system/link-module#known}">
This hiding and showing is achieved using the <gale:a
href="../gale/system/link-module">'link' module</gale:a>:

<pre>
&lt;gale:a href="howitworks"
        exec="${_personal#menu} = false;">
    hide the menu&lt;/gale:a>
</pre>
</gale:if>
</gale:then><gale:else>
<gale:a href="../howitworks" exec="${../_personal#menu} = true;">Showing the
menu</gale:a> is easy.
<gale:if expr="${../gale/gale-code#known-all} &amp;&amp; ${../gale/system/link-module#known}">
This hiding and showing is achieved using the <gale:a
href="../gale/system/link-module">'link' module</gale:a>:

<pre>
&lt;gale:a href="howitworks"
        exec="${_personal#menu} = true;">
    Showing the menu&lt;/gale:a>
</pre>
</gale:if>
</gale:else></gale:if>

The header at the top contains some functions in a small menu on the right. The menu
allows access to the comments panel on the right, you can reset your profile (starting the
adaptation from scratch), and logout. Resetting your profile is not a good idea. It will
erase all your knowledge (about this thesis, only in my user profile). Only use this when
you really want to start over. The CSS file mentioned before
(<a><gale:attr-variable name="href" expr="${../thesis}.getUri().resolve(&quot;thesis.css&quot;)" />thesis.css</a>)
is used to layout the various components on the screen through &lt;div>
sections in the HTML.
<gale:a adapt="false" href="../howitworks?external=http://www.w3.org/TR/css3-mediaqueries/">
Media queries
</gale:a> are used
to change the layout based on detected screen resolution and/or device. This includes the
location of the menu, comments and optionally the review path. To experience the
difference, view this thesis on a mobile device.</gale:text>

</gale:repo>
