<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">using a GUI to create a domain and
adaptation model</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;long" type="creole">The [[grapple|GRAPPLE]] Authoring Tools allow
the creation of a domain model and associated adaptation using a GUI
[[../references?tags=DeBra10|[DeBra10~]]]. The tools were developed by several partners in
the GRAPPLE project. As they are developed within the GRAPPLE project they are
mostly used in a Technology-Enhanced Learning setting.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">An author first creates a conceptual domain model
(CDM, or DM for short) for the application, consisting of concepts and concept
relationships. Relationships are named binary connections between concepts. The
relationships have a meaning within the application (course) domain, but they have no
associated adaptation behavior because they are not //pedagogical// relationships. To some
extent a domain model can be considered as an ontology, although typically it is smaller
and more easy for authors to create, as it only describes what is used in the course.
The figure below shows a partial domain model in the DM editor of GAT.

{{images/gat-dm.jpg|Domain Model Tool of GAT}}

It shows an example application called 'Milkyway'. In the Figure we see the Sun, planets
and moons and relationships like 'isMoonOf', connecting moons with their planet, and
'typeOf' connecting moons with the abstract concept 'Moon' and connecting planets with the
abstract concept 'Planet'. Some parts of the model in this figure are incomplete:
'isPlanetOf' relationships between planets and the Sun are still missing, as are some
moons. Each concept in DM can have an arbitrary number of properties with values, and
resources (references to files) with properties and values. The properties can be used by
the adaptation engine, for instance to select a resource to show depending on some user
model properties.

The author then needs to define a pedagogical structure over the DM, indicating
recommended ways to study the course. Using the CRT editor an author can create Concept
Relationship Types. Some CRTs are predefined, like //start// (for the start concept of a
course), //prerequisite// that indicates that some concepts should be studied before some
other concepts, and the //knowledge propagation// CRT that indicates that knowledge
obtained by studying course pages should be propagated up the concept hierarchy, typically
consisting of chapters, sections, subsections and pages. An author may thus not need to
define new CRTs to achieve the desired adaptation. Concepts from DM are connected using
CRTs to form the [[cam|Conceptual Adaptation Model]] (or CAM)
[[../references?tags=Hend08|[Hend08~]]]. In the [[../aha/graph-author|Graph Author]] CRTs
were either unary or binary relationships between single concepts. In GRAPPLE a concept
relationship can connect any arbitrary number of concepts or even sets of concepts. For
this it uses sockets each containing one or more concepts. The figure below shows a first
part of the CAM for the Milkyway example.

{{images/gat-cam.jpg|Conceptual Adaptation Model Tool}}

Allowing sockets with multiple concepts allows for the creation of CRTs with associated
adaptation rules that take all concepts of a socket into account. Also, it greatly reduced
the number of relationship (instances) that need to be created. When the CAM has been
completed the author selects the 'Deploy' function. This sends the CAM to GALE for
[[cam-compiler|compilation]].

The Domain Model tool was developed by Michele Dicerto of Giunti Labs, the CRT tool was
developed by Alexander Nussbaumer of the University of Graz and the CAM tool was developed
by Maurice Hendrix and Jonathan Foss of the University of Warwick.</gale:text>

</gale:repo>