<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole"></gale:text>

<gale:text tag="long" type="creole"></gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">When a new research field reaches a certain
maturity, it is a good idea to take a step back and look at what has been accomplished. In
the area of [[../research|adaptive hypermedia]] several good sources exist. These sources
are a great aid in determining the components of a //generic// adaptive hypermedia
system. Over time the methods and techniques to provide adaptation have increased. Our
better understanding of the machanics that drive an AHS has had a great influence on the
design of [[../aha|AHA!]] and [[../gale|GALE]].

One of the first comprehensive surveys on AHS by Peter Brusilovsky
[[../references?tags=Brus96-2|[Brus96-2~]]] contained the following taxonomy of adaptation
techniques:

{{images/tax-brusilovsky-1.jpg|Early taxonomy by Peter Brusilovsky}}

Most AHS at that time implemented these adaptation techniques or a subset of them. In the
5 years following 1996 many new AHS were developed. According to
[[../references?tags=Brus01|[Brus01~]]] two factors contributed to the rapid growth of the
research: "The first factor is the rapid increase in the use of the World Wide Web. The
Web, with its clear demand for adaptivity due to its widely diverse audience served to
boost adaptive hypermedia research, pro- viding both a challenge and an attractive
platform. Almost all the papers published before 1996 describe classic pre-Web hypertext
and hypermedia. In contrast, the majority of papers published since 1996 are devoted to
Web-based adaptive hypermedia systems. The second factor is the accumulation and
consolidation of research experience in the field. It is clearly visible that research in
adaptive hypermedia performed and reported up to 1996 has provided a good foundation for
the new generation of research. . . . The early papers provided no (or almost no)
references to similar work in adaptive hypermedia, and described original methods and
techniques. Almost all the systems developed by 1996 were laboratory systems developed to
demonstrate and explore innovative ideas. In contrast, many papers published since 1996
are clearly based on earlier research. These papers cite earlier work, and usually suggest
an elaboration or an extension of techniques suggested earlier. In addition, a large
number of systems developed since 1996 are either real world systems, or research systems
developed for real world settings. This is indicative of the relative maturity of adaptive
hypermedia as a research direction."

A new taxonomy in [[../references?tags=Brus01|[Brus01~]]] included adaptation techniques
found in the newer generation of AHS:

{{images/tax-brusilovsky-2.jpg|Taxonomy by Peter Brusilovsky}}

This taxonomy separates adaptation techniques in two areas: adaptive presentation and
adaptive navigation support. A more recent taxonomy in
[[../references?tags=Knutov09|[Knutov09~]]] takes another aspect into account, namely
content adaptation. An example would be inserting a fragment of text only for a particular
user or a set of users (based on their user model). Knutov's taxonomy takes into account
that some of the techniques could be called adaptive presentation and content adaptation.
There is some overlap between the three major techniques:

{{images/tax-knutov.jpg|Taxonomy by Evgeny Knutov}}

Since all adaptive hypermedia systems use hypermedia to present information to the user,
and the current standards are all based around (X)HTML, a system that allows arbitrary
manipulation of (X)HTML would be able to perform all of the techniques described above. Of
course, this definition would be valid for many systems, like Java servlets in general, or
PHP, JSP, Apache Wicket, XSLT (when XHTML is used), etc. They all allow generation and
manipulation of (X)HTML. The goal of AHA! and GALE was and is to allow all adaptation
techniques described here, with the least authoring effort possible, and to create a
simple yet powerful method of describing and refering to the domain and user model. In
GALE we realised 'adaptation inheritance', the process where one author can specify parts
of the adaptation and another author can reuse and build upon those
definitions.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole" expr="${../howitworks#new-content}">It might be
time to take another look at the '[[../howitworks|]]' topic. There is some more
information there now (as you can see by the link color). I have marked the new
information by drawing a line on the left side of it. <gale:if
expr="${../_personal#review}">Even though you are reviewing this thesis, it is ok to take
a look at this page. It will not have any effect on the rest of this thesis. Once you have
read the 'How It Works' page (by following the link above), I will lead you back to the
next topic.</gale:if> </gale:text>

</gale:repo>