<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">the process of changing the content of a
resource to make it more suitable for a particular user</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="long" type="creole">Determining how the content of a resource should be
adapted for a specific user is a process that strongly depends on the type of content. To
support adaptation of HTML, XHTML and XML, GALE includes [[system/processors]] that use
special instructions that the author embedded in the content. These instructions are for
example {{{&lt;gale:if expr="...">}}} or {{{&lt;gale:variable name="...">}}} and many
more. They allow parts of the actual content to depend on the [[domain-model|domain
model]] and [[user-model|user model]].</gale:text>
    
<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">Determining how the content of a resource should be
adapted for a specific user is a process that strongly depends on the type of content. As
an adaptive hypermedia server, GALE supports HTML, XHTML and XML by default. Through its
modular architecture GALE allows extensions to adapt other content as well.

HTML is first translated to XHTML, and XHTML is a form of XML. GALE introduces an XML
namespace ({{{http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation}}}) that contains tags that support adapting
the content based on the [[user-model|user model]] and [[domain-model|domain model]]. Some
of the tags can be used in any form of XML, while others are only meaningful in XHTML.
<gale:if expr="${system/processors#known}"> In the description of each module we indicate
which forms of XML can be adapted by that module.</gale:if>

Here is an example of how to use these tags to conditionally include a piece of
content:

{{{
&lt;html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
      xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">
  &lt;body>
    &lt;gale:if expr="${#visited} &lt;= 1">Welcome to this site for the first time!&lt;/gale:if>
    Make your selection of beers in the options below:
  &lt;/body>
&lt;/html>
}}}

The language used to create expressions is [[gale-code|GALE (EL) code]]. The various tags
available are these:
* [[system/if-module|&lt;gale:if>]], conditionally include a piece of XML based on an
  expression.
* [[system/object-module|&lt;gale:object>]], include the content of another concept or
  file in the current XML document.
* [[system/link-module|&lt;gale:a>]], create an adaptive link to another concept.
* [[system/variable-module|&lt;gale:variable>]], insert the result of an expression as
  text.
* [[system/attr-variable-module|&lt;gale:attr-variable>]], insert the result of an
  expression as attribute in the parent tag.
* [[system/for-module|&lt;gale:for>]], loops over the contents of the associated XML
  element to include it multiple times.
* [[system/text-module|&lt;gale:text>]], allows taggable blocks of text written using
  different syntax and converted to XHTML.
* [[system/repo-module|&lt;gale:repo>]], creates a repository of text fragments.
* [[system/count-module|&lt;gale:count>]], counts the number of visited or still to read
  concepts.
* [[system/test-module|&lt;gale:test>]], creates a multiple choice test and makes the
  result available in the user model.
* [[system/plugin-module|&lt;gale:plugin>]], creates a link to a
  [[system/processors|plugin]].
* [[system/view-module|&lt;gale:view>]], generating X(HT)ML based on the current
  concept, domain and user model.
* [[system/html-module|'html' module]], used to support some of GALE's functions.

</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="analytic" type="creole">There are many frameworks that provide the ability
to alter parts of an (X)HTML document programmatically before it is served to the client,
e.g. [[=http://www.php.net/|PHP]], [[=http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=245|JSP]],
[[=http://wicket.apache.org|Apache Wicket]], etc. Specifications like
[[=http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt|XSLT]] can be used to describe how a particular XML document
should be transformed. Though these techniques could be used to perform adaptation to
(X)HTML, there are several reasons why GALE does not use any of these at the moment.

GALE has roots in [[../aha|AHA!]], a project that predates many of the techniques that are
currently available. XML and XSLT were emerging technologies at the time and
[[../research/early-aha|early versions]] of AHA! focused on HTML. As authors came up with
new ideas, new tags were invented along the way. When the focus shifted to adapting XML,
using an in-memory DOM tree was easier to implement than SAX processing. There was no
compelling reason to change that later on. Authors seemed quickly familiar with the
various tags available in GALE. Some GALE constructs, like conditional object inclusion,
are difficult to mimic with other frameworks.

All of the functionality described in this section is handled by a single GALE
[[system/processors|processor]]<gale:if expr="!${system/processors#known}"> (a component
in the GALE <gale:a href="system/adaptation-engine">Adaptation Engine</gale:a> that is
part of the processing stack)</gale:if>. This type of component can be swapped without
even recompiling GALE. This allows for future implementations that do use SAX processing,
XSLT, or any of the other options. Not all implementations need to support the same
functionality. </gale:text>

</gale:repo>