<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole"></gale:text>

<gale:text tag="long" type="creole"></gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">Hypertext has proven its value in many
applications, including Technology-Enhanced Learning. Traditional paper textbooks present
material in a single order, which is supposedly the best order for studying. In a
hypertext, cross-references or links allow more freedom to navigate the material. An
adaptive hypertext takes information about the reader into account when presenting the
material including the cross-references. Actions taken by the reader (e.g. following a
link) can update the information on the reader, hence change the adaptation.

Over the years many different adaptive hypermedia systems have been developed. These
systems vary in the way the user is modeled and how that can affect the actual
presentation. They are, for the most part, able to perform particular types of adaptation
well, but are not compatible with each other. Furthermore, when compared to a traditional
web server, an adaptive web server has more work to do. This has often led to performance
issues, making the adoption of adaptive hypertext less likely.

GALE (Generic Adaptation Language and Engine) is the result of the ongoing research effort
to create an efficient generic adaptive hypermedia system (AHS) that is simple to use yet
powerful in expressing adaptation. It is able to emulate most of the adaptation found in
other AHS. The performance of GALE allows for a browsing experience similar to that of a
normal web server. Adaptive behavior can be inherited allowing different types of authors,
both beginner and advanced, to use adaptivity. The description that constitutes the
adaptive behavior can be distributed over multiple computers and maintained by multiple
authors. The modular structure of GALE allows extensions, integration with other systems
and the various components can be distributed to run on different computers.

This thesis describes the historical background of GALE and motivates its design
decisions. It shows how lessons learned from its predecessor AHA! have been implemented.
The current state of GALE is described to demonstrate its expressive power. As proof of
the pudding this thesis is served adaptively by GALE. </gale:text>

</gale:repo>