<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">bundling the .gam files together with the
actual content</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;long" type="creole">An author of an adaptive GALE application has
the option of placing the .gam files in the same location as the content. This will make
the application available to any GALE server. Editing the .gam files in place will be
recognized by GALE and any updates are processed almost instantly.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">One of GALE's [[../system/services|services]]
attempts to discover a GAM file that defines the concept identified by a specific URI, if
the URI is also a URL with the HTTP scheme. The discovery process can be
[[../system/configuration|configured]] to search for specifically named .gam files, by
default a file named 'concepts.gam'. The process starts the search in the same path as the
concept URI. If no file was found that contained a definition for the concept, it moves up
one level in the path. This continues until such a file is found or the root of the path
is reached, in which case the concept does not exist (according to discovery).

Assuming there is a request for a concept named
{{{http://starwars.org/sides/empire/leaders/darth-vader}}}, discovery will search the
following files:
* {{{http://starwars.org/sides/empire/leaders/concepts.gam}}}
* {{{http://starwars.org/sides/empire/concepts.gam}}}
* {{{http://starwars.org/sides/concepts.gam}}}
* {{{http://starwars.org/concepts.gam}}}

If {{{http://starwars.org/sides/empire/concepts.gam}}} contained a definition for the
'darth-vader' concept, discovery will not load the final two files.

The concepts defined in a GAM file can use relative URIs. For instance,

{{{ leaders/darth-vader {
    ...
} }}}

in the file {{{http://starwars.org/sides/empire/concepts.gam}}} will define the
'darth-vader' concept described above.

==== $options concept ====

Bundled GAM files can set options at any point in the file where a concept is expected.
Options are set by including a concept named '$options'. The properties of this concept
are used as follows:
|=property name     |=property value
|default.properties |a semicolon (;) separated list of properties that should be inherited by default
|default.order      |set to 'auto' to create 'order' properties for every concept based on the actual order inside the GAM file
|parent             |relative or absolute URI that should be used in discovering associated GAM files
|module             |relative or absolute URI that should be used in discovering associated GAM files

The 'parent' and 'module' directives are semantically equivalent. It might be necessary to
include these in a GAM file, when relations need to be available that are defined
elsewhere. Authors should be careful to only use this option to include files they have
created themselves, as GALE will load all associated GAM files (and their associated GAM
files, etc.), when the requested file is loaded. The following scenario demonstrates when
this might be necessary.

**File: {{{http://starwars.org/sides/empire/leaders/concepts.gam}}}** {{{ darth-vader {
    ->(parent)../leaders ...
} }}}

**File: {{{http://starwars.org/sides/empire/concepts.gam}}}** {{{ leaders {
    ...
} }}}

If somebody were to request the concept {{{http://starwars.org/sides/empire/leaders}}},
the parent relation defined in {{{http://starwars.org/sides/empire/leaders/concepts.gam}}}
will not be available, hence the 'leaders' concept will not have any children. Changing
{{{http://starwars.org/sides/empire/concepts.gam}}} to the following will force GALE to
read the 'leaders/concepts.gam' file:

{{{ $options {
    module "leaders"
}

leaders {
    ...
} }}}

Forcing GALE to read module and parent GAM files allows relations to be discovered even if
they are defined in a file that does not contain the currently requested
concept.</gale:text>

</gale:repo>