<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole"></gale:text>

<gale:text tag="long" type="creole"></gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">During my Computer Science study I came into
contact with the group of people conducting adaptive hypermedia research at the Eindhoven
University of Technology. They were looking for someone to implement a new generic system
for adaptive hypermedia. This appeared to be a suitable topic for an internship and I have
been interested in adaptive hypermedia ever since.

First and foremost I would like to thank my promoter Paul De Bra for being a great
supervisor and mentor, for our regular discussions on adaptive hypermedia (as many ideas
described in this thesis originate from those) and for allowing me to discover the merits
of writing documentation (as opposed to only designing and implementing software) at my
own pace. This thesis and underlying software would not exist without him.

I would like to express my gratitude to the members of the reading committee: Hans
Cuypers, Nicola Henze, Mykola Pechenizkiy and Vincent Wade, for their many comments that
helped improve the quality of this thesis. In particular, I thank Vincent for not only
commenting on the contents but also on the usability of the adaptive hypertext.

The work presented in this thesis took place within the scope of many projects,
specifically the AHA! project and GRAPPLE. I would like to thank Stichting NLnet and the
European Commission for their financial support, the many partners in the GRAPPLE project
for their contributions that helped shape GALE and the Eindhoven University of Technology
for being a flexible organization where I was able to perform most of my research
part-time.

In the course of the past ten years I met many people working in the area of adaptive
hypermedia who have affected my work. Many thanks go to Natasha Stash for her programming
on AHA! and her enthusiasm for adaptive hypermedia, to Alexandra Cristea for her ideas on
languages to describe adaptive behavior and to Alexandros Paramythis for his great help
and expertise in programming with Java, which motivated me to use software libraries
whenever possible. I would like to thank Riet van Buul and Ine van der Ligt for their
great administrative skills and support.

I owe a debt of gratitude to my parents, Martin and Sibilla Smits, who have always
supported me. I would not have finished my Computer Science study if it wasn’t for my
father’s persistent effort to motivate me. Finally I would like to give special thanks to
my wife Jenny who had to miss me more than usual these past few months.

David Smits

Landgraaf, February 2012 </gale:text>

</gale:repo>