<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">a simple expression language to allow
easy access to [[domain-model|domain]] and [[user-model|user model]]</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="long" type="creole">GALE code is Java source code enhanced with a special
syntax to access the [[user-model|user model]] and [[domain-model|domain model]]. The code
is written by authors of adaptive applications and executed by GALE.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="intro" type="creole">Creating an adaptive course or web application
requires some automated process to update the user model whenever that is deemed necessary
by the author. Adaptive hypermedia systems differ greatly in the amount of control they
give to the author when updating the user model and using this model to adapt content,
presentation, etc.

To allow any current and future system to be simulated by GALE, //it allows any adaptation
that can be programmed//. Though the language used can be changed by replacing a GALE
module called the [[system/codemanager|'Code Manager']], the default will be sufficient in
most cases. Java (1.5) is used as the default programming language. To simplify authoring
the most common adaptation rules, a special syntax allows easy access to domain and user
model.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">Almost any Java code can be written where GALE code
is expected. Some code may be rejected or cause an exception when run because of security
restrictions (e.g. it is not allowed to access the file system of the GALE server). To
access the [[gel/gel|GALE Expression Language (GEL)]] the syntax {{{${ ... ~}}}} is used.
The idea to use this syntax is taken from the
[[=http://java.sun.com/products/jsp/syntax/2.0/syntaxref207.html#1010522|JSP
EL]]. The GEL syntax can be [[gel/usage|mixed]] with the rest of the Java
code.

GALE code can be used to express both statements and expressions. The context determines
which one is required. [[gam/syntax|Event code]] in the [[domain-model|domain model]]
should be statement code, whereas [[gam/attribute|default values]] for attributes should
be expressions. Everytime an expression is required you can optionally include a tilde
(~~) at the start of the expression to build a complex function. This thesis contains
something that looks like the following function to determine the resource associated with
a concept:

{{{
#resource ='~~
    if (${#suitability})
        return ${.}.getUri()+".xml";
    else
        return "unsuitable.xml";
'
}}}

GALE code is often used when writing resources (the actual content) for an application.
Various [[modifying-resource|modules]] are available that allow adaptation to the content
of XML and XHTML/HTML pages. The [[system/if-module|if module]] and
[[system/variable-module|variable module]] are some examples.

{{{
&lt;p>Hi, &lt;gale:variable expr="${gale://gale.tue.nl/personal#name}" />.
    &lt;gale:if expr="${#visited} &lt; 3">&lt;b>Read these instructions carefully!&lt;/b>&lt;/gale:if>
&lt;/p>
}}}

This example retrieves the name stored in the 'gale:~//gale.tue.nl/personal' concept.
Depending on how often you have 'visited' the current concept the string 'Read these
instructions carefully' is shown.</gale:text>

</gale:repo>