<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">a language used for describing the domain
and adaptation model aimed at being human readable/writable</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="intro" type="creole">Many tools exist to author domain models, but few
take adaptation into account. Hence, adaptive hypermedia systems often come with their own
authoring tools. Early versions of [[../research/early-aha|AHA!]] relied on text editors
to author adaptivity in some format supported by the system. [[../aha|Later versions]]
contained (graphical) tools to help authoring domain models. For [[../gale|GALE]]
graphical tools were created in the [[../research/grapple|]] project.

Though some authors welcome the aid of a graphical tool, others will prefer to author the
code that drives adaptivity directly. This has the added benefit of using your own
preferred (possibly feature-rich) text editor. Since some form of editor is used to create
the actual content of the application anyway, it has advantages to be able to author the
domain model using the same tool.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="long" type="creole">The GALE Adaptation Model (GAM) aims to be a human
readable/writable language allowing the definition of domain concepts and associated
adaptation. </gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">The GALE Adaptation Model (GAM) aims to be a human
readable/writable language allowing the definition of domain concepts and associated
adaptation. GAM is a purely textual format. The language is one of the
[[domain-model|domain model]] formats supported by GALE. GAM can be [[gam/usage|bundled]]
together with the content of the application. The [[gam/syntax|syntax]] relies heavely on
[[gale-code|GALE code]]. GAM can also be used as a basis for [[gam/external-tools|external
tools]], like authoring tools or converters. An example is the <a
href="gam/gam-syntax-0.9.0-ko.xpi">syntax highlighter</a> that can be used in
[[=http://www.activestate.com/komodo-edit|Komodo Edit]] version 6. A [[gam/formal|formal]]
description of the language will help in the creation of such tools.</gale:text>

</gale:repo>