<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">extending GALE to add new features using
Java code</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="long" type="creole">It is impossible to foresee future adaptation
techniques. Nor is it possible to implement every technique that is currently found in
other systems. GALE offers various extension points:
* modules, new X(HT)ML content adaptation
* views, new X(HT)ML content/presentation generation
* plugins, new actions to be taken when the request URL indicates the use of a plugin
* services, new ways to respond to GALE events
* processors, new document formats to adapt or new pre and post processing
* login, new methods of identifying the user
* code, changing the underlying language used by GALE to express adaptivity</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">GALE is built from the ground up with extension in
mind. Being a //generic// engine for adaptation, implies offering possibilities for future
formats and techniques to be incorporated. To that end, various functions of GALE have
been abstracted and separated from other functions.

Instead of only stating that it is easy to extend GALE, we offer some example extensions
to demonstrate this statement. The examples are fairly technical in nature, because they
represent all that is required to extend GALE, including the Java code that needs to be
written. For some readers it may suffice to see the short length of code required to
extend GALE:
* [[extending-module|]], handling specific tags in XML or XHTML.
* [[extending-view|]], generating content based on the request, DM and UM.
* [[extending-plugin|]], direct control over a user's HTTP request.
* [[extending-service|]], responding to events from the Adaptation Engine or other
  services.
* [[extending-processor|]], handling new types of content or changing specific parts of
  processing resources.
* [[extending-login|]], allowing new methods of identifying a user.
* [[extending-code|]], replacing the default implementation of Java as the language to
  describe adaptivity. </gale:text>

</gale:repo>