<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">allowing taggable blocks of text written
using different syntax and converted to XHTML</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="long" type="creole">{{{
&lt;gale:text type="creole">
[[brand|Brand]] is a [[beer]] that is brewed in Limburg.
&lt;/gale:text>
}}}

The {{{&lt;gale:text>}}} tag allows a wiki syntax where links are interpreted as links to
concepts instead of resources. The text blocks can be tagged using the {{{tag}}}
attribute. Based on \UM and \DM different tags can be displayed or hidden. An optional
{{{expr}}} attribute allows additional control over the visibility of text
blocks.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole" expr="${processors#known}">The 'text' module allows
taggable blocks of text written using different syntax and coverted to XHTML. The
[[configuration|configuration]] links the 'text' module to the &lt;gale:text> tag. By
default the only valid mime type is:
* "text/xhtml"</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">XHTML is like XML verbose in its markup. When
authoring large adaptive applications, other, less verbose formats are practical. The
{{{&lt;gale:text>}}} tag allows other formats to be included inline and converted on the
fly. In particular [[../../gale|GALE]] supports [[=http://www.wikicreole.org|Creole]],
which is an attempt to create a Wiki standard. Some extentions are added to support the
adaptive nature of the target XHTML.

A {{{&lt;gale:text>}}} block can optionally be tagged by providing a 'tag' attribute. The
value of the attribute is a semicolon separated list of tags associated with the
particular block. Blocks will only be included if at least one of the tags is in the value
of the {{{#tags}}} attribute.

The {{{#tags}}} attribute should define a string value representing a semicolon separated
list of tags. A wildcard '*' in the list means any tag is included. A hyphen '-' in front
of a tag name in the list means no block is included that contains that tag.

This thesis uses the following definition for the {{{#tags}}} attribute using
[[../gam|GAM]] code:

{{{
#tags ='~
    if (${#visited} > 3) return "-intro;-short;*";
    if ("true".equals(${?intro-first}))
        return (${#visited} > 1?"-intro;-short;*":"intro");
    return "-short;*";
'
}}}

This would result in the following behavior. Never show blocks tagged with 'short'. If you
have seen the concept at least 3 times, stop showing blocks tagged with 'intro'. If the
concept is marked as 'intro-first', then on the first request only show 'intro' blocks.
After that stop showing the 'intro' blocks.

Using this code allows an author to create blocks that are normally never shown (the
'short' blocks). However, the tags that are actually shown can be overridden using a
request parameter 'tags'. This allows the inclusion of parts of the content of one concept
in another concept:

{{{
&lt;gale:object name="beer?tags=short&amp;no-update=true" />
}}}

The 'no-update' parameter is included to prevent GALE from processing the object inclusion
as a concept access, which would normally result in UM updates.

An optional expression can be attached to a {{{&lt;gale:text>}}} block to prevent it from
showing regardless of tags. The expression should be placed in an 'expr' attribute. The
following two examples behave identically:

{{{
&lt;gale:text tag="details" expr="${beer#known}">
...
&lt;/gale:text>
}}}

{{{
&lt;gale:if expr="${beer#known}">
    &lt;gale:text tag="details">
    ...
    &lt;/gale:text>
&lt;/gale:if>
}}}

=== Creole ===

If the text type is omitted, the content of a {{{&lt;gale:text>}}} block should be XHTML.
By marking the block as 'creole' the content can be written in wiki style. Simply include
a 'type="creole"' attribute:

{{{
&lt;gale:text type="creole">
[[brand|Brand]] is a [[beer]] that is brewed in Limburg.
&lt;/gale:text>
}}}

This example will result in the following XHTML:

{{{
&lt;p>&lt;a xmlns="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation" href="brand">Brand&lt;/a> is a
&lt;a xmlns="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation" href="beer">beer&lt;/a> that is brewed in Limburg.&lt;/p>
}}}

Notice that links in Creole are translated to GALE links to concepts. A special feature is
a link where the title of the target concept is used as text. To use this feature, append
'|' at the end. {{{[[text-module|]]}}} would result in this XHTML:

{{{
&lt;a xmlns="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation" href="text-module">
&lt;variable xmlns="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation" expr="${text-module}.getTitle()" />
&lt;/a>
}}}

External links use the {{{[[=...]]}}} notation.
{{{[[=http://www.wikicreole.org|Creole]]}}} will result in the following XHTML:

{{{
&lt;a xmlns="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation" href="?external=http://www.wikicreole.org" adapt="false">Creole&lt;/a>
}}}

</gale:text>

</gale:repo>