<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">researching the possibility of creating a
usable generic adaptive hypermedia system that performs well</gale:text>

<gale:if expr="${appendix/title#own-knowledge} == 0"><gale:object name="appendix/title" /></gale:if>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">
== Towards a Generic Distributed Adaptive Hypermedia Environment ==

Hypertext has proven its value in many applications, including Technology-Enhanced
Learning. Traditional paper textbooks present material in a single order, which is
supposedly the best order for studying. In a hypertext, cross-references or links allow
more freedom to navigate the material. An adaptive hypertext takes information about the
reader into account when presenting the material including the cross-references. Actions
taken by the reader (eg. following a link) can update the user model, hence change the
adaptation.

Over the years many different adaptive hypermedia systems have been developed. These
systems vary in the way the user is modelled and how that can affect the actual
presentation. They are, for the most part, able to perform particular types of adaptation
well, but are not compatible with each other. Furthermore, when compared to a traditional
web server, an adaptive web server has more work to do. This has often led to performance
issues, making the adoption of adaptive hypertext less likely.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">In this thesis we present the current state of
[[gale|GALE]], a generic Adaptive Hypermedia System (AHS). GALE is the result of its
predecessor [[aha|AHA!]] and [[research|adaptive hypermedia research]]. It is a fully
functional and extensible AHS. The various research [[research/projects|projects]] that
enabled the development of AHA! and GALE, provided valuable input for the use cases of a
generic AHS. Though we believe GALE is a feature-rich system, there are still ideas that
require [[future-work|future work]].</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole" expr="${introduction#knowledge} &lt; 0.5">Before
diving into the full breadth and depth of the material, we recommend reading through the
[[introduction]]. <gale:if expr="!${introduction#known}">(We actually disable most of the
content if you have not read the introduction, not just because we can.)</gale:if> It will
give you a good idea of the [[questions]] that motivated the research and development
described along the way. We provide a 'hyper'-adaptive page entitled '[[howitworks|How It
Works]]'. This page will explain the inner workings of adaptivity as it is found in this
thesis. The contents will change over time as your (presumed) knowledge on methods and
techniques of adaptivity increase.</gale:text>

</gale:repo>
