<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">the
[[=http://www.grapple-project.org|GRAPPLE project]] and it's impact on the development of
[[../gale|GALE]]</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">[[=http://www.grapple-project.org|GRAPPLE]]
(Generic Responsive Adaptive Personalized Learning Environment)
[[../references?tags=DeBra12|[DeBra12~]]] is an EU FP7 STREP project that ran from
February 1, 2008 to January 31, 2011. As described in the
[[=http://www.grapple-project.org/summary|project summary]], twelve academic and three
industrial partners collaborated to develop a generic adaptive learning environment (GALE)
and integrate it with (five) different learning management systems (LMS) in order to
enable adaptive life-long learning for learners in higher education and industry. We
include the architectural overview image here:

{{images/grapple-architecture.jpg|Overview of the GRAPPLE Architecture}} </gale:text>

<gale:text tag="long;default" type="creole">GRAPPLE designed and built an architecture
that consists of:
* LMS for managing the learning process, progress and support,
* [[../gale|GALE]] for the adaptive delivery of learning material,
* [[gumf|GUMF]], a generic User Model Framework that maintains information about each
  learner as (s)he uses different LMS and GALE instances,
* a single sign-on facility (based on [[=http://shibboleth.internet2.edu/|Shibboleth]])
  that ensures that all GRAPPLE components recognize the learner through a single
  identity,
* GEB, a generic Event Bus that facilitates asynchronous information exchange between all
  GRAPPLE components,
* [[gat|GAT]], an authoring tool used to create an adaptive course.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole"><gale:if expr="${als#known}"><gale:then>As we have
seen in the <gale:a href="als">ALS project</gale:a>, <gale:a href="../aha">AHA!</gale:a>
went through some architectural changes to allow the integration with
Sakai.</gale:then><gale:else>In the earlier <gale:a href="als">ALS project</gale:a>,
<gale:a href="../aha">AHA!</gale:a> was already transformed from a single monolithic
adaptation engine to a more modularized version that could be integrated in an LMS
(Sakai).</gale:else></gale:if> In GRAPPLE, development on this version of AHA! continued,
which eventually lead to [[../gale|GALE]]. Some explanations in the subsections of the
GRAPPLE project, especially the section on [[gumf|GUMF]], depend on your knowledge of
GALE.</gale:text>

</gale:repo>