<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">the Adaptive Learning Spaces (ALS)
project and its impact on AHA!'s development</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">As described on the project site, the goal of the
[[=http://www.als-project.org/|Adaptive Learning Spaces]] (ALS) project is: "To provide
the technological means through which lack of (or limited amounts of) face-to-face contact
between instructors and learners, as well as amongst learners can be partially compensated
for. To achieve this, ALS will work towards: (a) widening the range of, as well as
increasing the amount of, guidance and support that Open Distance Learning (ODL) systems
can provide to learners and instructors, and (b) providing novel means to support the
social cohesion of groups of learners, as well as the engagement of their members in
collaborative/team tasks and processes.

This will be achieved by developing, field-testing and making openly available a software
infrastructure that builds upon the state-of-the-art in the fields of e-learning and
adaptive hypermedia systems, to support the creation of active, personalised learning
spaces, that will have a clear focus on learning activities, treating learners as active
members of, and contributors to, their learning environments, rather than as passive
recipients of their contents."

The project required the integration of [[../aha|AHA!]], a Learning Management System
([[=http://www.sakaiproject.org|Sakai]]) and several collaboration tools. The
collaboration tools use information stored in AHA! to determine expert learners on a
particular domain. This required that AHA! would be able to share user and domain model
information. The [[grapple|GRAPPLE project]] has a similar requirement. The output of ALS
includes an intermediate version of AHA! that has some of the features found in
[[../gale|GALE]].

<gale:if expr="!${../aha/system#known-all}">The <gale:a href="../aha/system">AHA!
engine</gale:a> was changed considerably to support this integration. When you know more
about the engine, I will explain the details of the required
changes.</gale:if></gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole" expr="${../aha/system#known-all}">AHA! (version 4)
was only released as an embedded tool within Sakai. Some of the improvements that can also
be found in GALE are:
* The domain and adaptation models were [[../gale/domain-model|extended]], including
  concepts identified by a URI, [[../gale/adaptation-model|any Java code]] as adaptation
  rules, and arbitrary relations as part of the domain model. This allowed concepts (and
  the associated user model data) to be more uniquely identified across different AHA!
  servers.
* AHA! was [[../gale/system|split]] in several components that communicate over an
  [[../gale/system/events|event bus]]. This allowed a more open architecture where user
  model and domain model are accessible and update-able by other components within Sakai.
* The functionality in the [[../aha/engine|content handlers]] of AHA! was modularized.
  This allowed the easy creation of [[../gale/system/extending-module|new XML modules]],
  [[../gale/system/extending-view|new views]], [[../gale/system/extending|etc.]]
  
</gale:text>

</gale:repo>