<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">translating the input from a [[cam|.cam
XML]] file to [[../gale/domain-model|GALE concepts]]</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;long" type="creole">The CAM compiler is part of [[../gale|GALE]].
It will interpret a [[cam|.cam XML]] file to create the neccesary
[[../gale/domain-model|GALE concepts]]. This involves expanding the
[[../gale/gam/external-tools|parameterized GAM]] so that it is incorporated in the proper
concepts as defined by the course model.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">All domain model terms defined in the .cam will
become concepts in GALE. On this set of concepts the CRTs are interpreted one by one. Some
information in the CRT is straightforward, like the addition of new attributes through the
user model definitions. These definitions are attached to one of the sockets of the CRT.
All the concepts that are in the socket in the course model, will have their definition
updated to include these user model attributes.

The interpretation of the GAM code will be explained using the following example:

{{images/compiler-crt.jpg|One prerequisite definition in the course model}}

The prerequisite described here defines that 'Sun and Planet' must be studied before any
of the planets 'Mercury, Venus or Earth'. We assume the CRT is defined as can be seen in
the [[cam|.cam XML]] description. This includes the following GAM code:

{{{
%target% {
  #suitability:Boolean &amp;='(${%source%#knowledge}>%level%)'
  #[knowledge]:Float
}
}}}

The compiler needs to interpret the CRT code for every possible combination of concepts in
the sockets. In this example it would be:

|=step    |=source    |=target    |
|1        |Sun        |Mercury    |
|2        |Sun        |Venus      |
|3        |Sun        |Earth      |
|4        |Planet     |Mercury    |
|5        |Planet     |Venus      |
|6        |Planet     |Earth      |

When the code is applied to the first combination in the list, the parameters are replaced
by their instantiated concepts. The %level% is a CRT parameter. In the course model the
author will have provided a value for it. We assume a value of 0.8.

{{{
Mercury {
  #suitability:Boolean &amp;='(${Sun#knowledge}>0.8)'
  #[knowledge]:Float
}
}}}

This GAM code will update the concept definition of Mercury. A {{{#suitability}}} and
{{{#knowledge}}} attribute will be added and {{{#knowledge}}} will be persisted in the
user model. The {{{#suitability}}} attribute will have a default expression of
{{{(${Sun#knowledge}>0.8)}}}. When the compiler reaches step 4 in the list, the following
code will be interpreted:

{{{
Mercury {
  #suitability:Boolean &amp;='(${Planet#knowledge}>0.8)'
  #[knowledge]:Float
}
}}}

The compiler will ignore instructions that do not update anything (like the definition of
{{{#knowledge}}} in this code). The {{{#suitability}}} attribute's default expression will
be updated to include the new part. The compiler uses the '&amp;=' instruction to combine
already existing expressions with the new part like this:

{{{
((${Sun#knowledge}>0.8)) &amp;&amp; ((${Planet#knowledge}>0.8))
}}}

The extra quotes are always added to ensure that the expression is really what the author
intended (though they could have been ommitted in this specific instance). The alternative
in the definition could have been:

{{{
#suitability:Boolean |='(${%source%#knowledge}>%level%)'
}}}

This would have combined the individual pieces using the {{{||}}} operator, reading either
Sun //or// Planet would satisfy the prerequisite. When the type of the attribute involved
is a String or a number, the {{{+=}}} operator allows the combination of pieces using
String concatenation or addition.

When all CRTs are interpreted the resulting set of concepts is added to (or updates) the
GALE database. <gale:if expr="${../gale/system/events#known-all}">A 'setdm' <gale:a
href="../gale/system/event-types">event</gale:a> is used to send the information to the
default <gale:a href="../gale/system/dm-service">DM
service</gale:a>.</gale:if></gale:text>

</gale:repo>