<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">developments that led to version 1 of
the [[../aha|Adaptive Hypermedia Architecture!]]</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="long" type="creole">The creation of a single adaptive hypermedia
application marked the beginning of AHA!. During its development, new options and
possibilities arose due to the development of the Web. </gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">The development of AHA! has always been
author-driven. The course 2L670, "Hypermedia Structures and Systems", has been available
on the World Wide Web since 1994 [[../references?tags=DeBra96|[DeBra96~]]] (it is still
available as
[[=http://wwwis.win.tue.nl:37080/gale/concept/gale://wwwis.win.tue.nl/2ID65/welcome|2ID65]],
served by [[../gale|GALE]]). To aid students in learning the material, adaptivity was
added to the course using the Unix C preprocessor in 1996
[[../references?tags=Calvi97|[Calvi97~]]]. The author would use a combination of {{{#if}}}
and {{{#ifdef}}} contructs to create basic adaptive content. This resulted in an authoring
environment in which two completely different syntaxes had to be mixed. To improve
authoring, the next version of the course and associated software used HTML comments.
[[../references?tags=DeBra97|[DeBra97~]]] describes an example using these comments. We
include a short version here:

{{{
&lt;!-- requires true -->
&lt;!-- generates index -->

  &lt;H1>Hypermedia structures and systems&lt;/H1> Welcome to course 2L690 at the
  Eindhoven University of Technology. &lt;P>

&lt;!-- if not readme -->

  Since you are just beginning to browse through this course, you should first read &lt;a
  href="readme.html">the instructions&lt;/a>. These will explain how to use this course
  text, together with a graphical World Wide Web browser such as the Netscape Navigator,
  Microsoft Internet Explorer, or NCSA Mosaic.

&lt;!-- else -->

  This course contains the following (not necessarily disjoint) parts:

&lt;!-- endif -->

  &lt;ul>
  &lt;li>&lt;a href="intro.html">Introduction&lt;/a>
    (it is advised to read this before the other items)
  &lt;li>&lt;a href="definition.html">Definition of hypertext and hypermedia&lt;/a>
  &lt;li>The &lt;a href="history.html">history&lt;/a> of hypertext and hypermedia

&lt;!-- if readme but not (introduction and definition and history) -->

  &lt;/ul>
  The following parts will become available later (when you are ready for them):
  &lt;ul>

&lt;!-- endif -->

  &lt;li>The &lt;a href="architecture.html">architecture&lt;/a> of hypertext systems
  &lt;li>&lt;a href="navigation.html">Navigation&lt;/a> (and browsing semantics) in hypertext
  ...
  &lt;/ul>
}}}

The first comment indicates what prior knowledge is required before this topic (or
concept) is recommended. The second comment links this page to a particular concept for
which knowledge is generated when the page is viewed. The //if//, //else// and //endif//
comments are used to selectively include content. Links are adapted when the 'href'
attribute is written in lowercase (uppercase 'HREF' links are not adapted).

One of the problems encountered while authoring an adaptive course with this system was in
its use of Booleans to express knowledge [[../references?tags=DeBra00|[DeBra00~]]]. For
instance, if some information in the document depended on having read a chapter of 5 pages
completely, the following requirement expression was necessery:

{{{
p1 and p2 and p3 and p4 and p5
}}}

Furthermore, the content HTML files contained conceptual information in the form of
requirements and knowledge generation statements. This method of describing the concept
structure in the same document as the content is similar to Interbook, where a Word
document contained content mixed with the concept definitions. However, creating a
conceptual structure is a different authoring activity then writing the actual content.
Hence, the information should reside in different files. An official version 1 of AHA!
improved authoring by making knowledge a number between 0 and 100, allowing knowledge
updates to trigger other updates and moving the requirements and knowledge generation
information to different files. These different files could look like this:

* generatelist.xml

{{{
&lt;genitem>
    &lt;name>heineken&lt;/name>
    &lt;genlist>beer:+20 alfa:-30&lt;/genlist>
&lt;/genitem>

&lt;genitem>
    &lt;name>alfa&lt;/name>
    &lt;genlist>beer:+80&lt;/genlist>
&lt;/genitem>
}}}

* requirements.xml

{{{
&lt;concept>
    &lt;conceptname>brewing&lt;/conceptname>
    &lt;relationexpression>beer >= 80&lt;/relationexpression>
&lt;/concept>
}}}

Learning something about 'heineken' will only contribute 20% of the knowledge to 'beer'.
You will 'unlearn' what you know about 'alfa' for 30% of whatever you learn about
'heineken'. 'alfa' contributes 80% of the knowledge to 'beer'. Before you can learn
anything about 'brewing' you need to understand 'beer' thoroughly (>=80).

These new definitions allowed greater authoring flexibility. Pages can contribute to
chapter knowledge and this chapter knowledge can be used in requirements. This propagation
of knowledge updates created the danger of infinite loops, as recursive updates were also
allowed (in some situations recursive updates are actually needed). Some steps were taken
to prevent an infinite loop from actually occuring
[[../references?tags=DeBra00|[DeBra00~]]]).

Making the software available for other authors has been a goal of [[../aha|AHA!]] and
[[../gale|GALE]] ever since. This means allowing as many [[taxonomy|adaptation
techniques]] as possible. 'The software and formats should be an "assembly language" of
adaptive hypermedia in the sense that any higher-level adaptation paradigm can be
expressed in terms of AHA! and simulated by the AHA! engine'
[[../references?tags=DeBra03-2|[DeBra03-2~]]]. The AHAM
[[../references?tags=Wu02|[Wu02~]]] reference model was a great help in understanding the
common properties of most adaptive hypermedia systems at that time. These early versions
of AHA! and the AHAM model contributed greatly to the design of [[../aha|AHA! 2 and
3]].</gale:text>

</gale:repo>