<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole"></gale:text>

<gale:text tag="long" type="creole"></gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">ELM-ART [[../references?tags=Brus96|[Brus96~]]],
Interbook [[../references?tags=Brus98|[Brus98~]]] and [[../aha|AHA!]] are examples of
systems that support //learning through adaptive information exploration//. The user
receives guidance (through link annotation and in AHA! also through the //conditional
inclusion of fragments//) but can browse through a course text in any desired way. More
support for the //process// of navigation and the use of //services// (going beyond the
single step of accessing a page) can be found for instance in APeLS, designed by Conlan
and Wade et al [[../references?tags=Conlan04|[Conlan04~]]].

Although adaptive applications in the field of E-Learning or "Technology-Enhanced
Learning" are the most common, there is also significant research in other application
areas. Personalized advertising is becoming big business. This is highly visible in
Google’s personalized ads, but also in recommendations on shopping sites, like the
//"people who bought this… also bought…"// messages on Amazon. Museums and other cultural
institutes are offering adaptive personalized previews and guided tours or are studying
this. The Dutch [[=http://www.nwo.nl/catch|CATCH]] (Continuous Access to Cultural
Heritage) research program has spawned a lot of research to improve access to cultural
information. In one of its projects: [[=http://chip-project.org/|CHIP]] (Cultural Heritage
Information Presentation and Personalization) a personalized art recommender was built for
(and jointly with) the Rijksmuseum [[../references?tags=Wang08|[Wang08~]]], as well as
personalized virtual and physical (mobile) guided tours
[[../references?tags=Hage10|[Hage10~]]]. Italy is also strong in the adaptive access to
information about culture and tourism, for instance through UbiquiTO, a multi-device
adaptive guide for Torino [[../references?tags=Amen04|[Amen04~]]] and the work on
Intelligent Inferfaces for Museum visitors from FBK in Trento
[[../references?tags=Kuflik11|[Kuflik11~]]]. The world of entertainment is following suit
with personalized TV guides such as [[=http://www.ifanzy.nl|iFanzy]]
[[../references?tags=Akker06|[Akker06~]]], a result of the ITEA Passepartout project.

The main difference between the mainstream adaptive educational applications and the
others is the role of the //author//. Systems for culture, entertainment and business are
typically large special-purpose Web-based Information Systems with an added
personalization or adaptation component. There is also a body of research towards making
Adaptive Web-based Information Systems more generic
[[../references?tags=Houben08;Rossi08|[Houben08, Rossi08~]]]. The definition of the
adaptation in Adaptive WIS is mostly automatically generated from semantic structures in
the databases. In Technology-Enhanced Learning a human author is involved in defining the
adaptation at the "instance level", specifying in detail how which action of the learner
leads to which change in the user model and how the user model state influences the
adaptation. But this is not only the case in Technology-Enhanced Learning. Adaptive
(adventure) games for instance also require carefully crafted adaptation rules.
[[../gale|GALE]] attempts to offer a //generic// solution to //authors// of adaptive
websites. In the [[grapple|GRAPPLE]] project (EU FP7 STREP) the //adaptation language//
and the graphical //authoring tools// played an important role. The GALE //engine// can be
used to serve information where the adaptation rules are generated from (semantic)
database structures.</gale:text>

</gale:repo>