<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">a module that allows adaptive links to
other concepts</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="long" type="creole">{{{
&lt;gale:a href="tour" exec="#{tour#start,true};">...&lt;/gale:a>
}}}

The {{{&lt;gale:a>}}} tag represents a link to a concept. The {{{href}}} attribute
contains a relative URI based on the current concept URI. The link can be annotated based
on an expression. Optionally [[../gale-code|GALE code]] can be included that is executed
when the link is followed.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole" expr="${processors#known}">The 'link' module allows
the creation of adaptive links to other concepts. The [[configuration|configuration]]
links the 'link' module to the &lt;gale:a> and &lt;gale:adapt-link> tags. By default the
only valid mime type is:
* "text/xhtml"</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">Link adaptation is the most common form of
adaptation in adaptive hypermedia systems. In GALE the {{{&lt;gale:a>}}} tag will be used
most often. There are several attributes that are meaningful:
* The {{{href}}} attribute is an absolute or relative URI of the target concept.
* The {{{exec}}} attribute contains optional [[../gale-code|GALE (EL) code]] that is
  executed when the link is clicked.
* The {{{adapt}}} attribute can be set to 'false' to indicate that no link adaptation
  should be performed. The {{{href}}} destination is still modified to reflect a link to a
  concept. This option is used to create links to concept that have static annotation.

{{{
&lt;gale:a href="welcome">...&lt;/gale:a>
}}}

This defines an adaptive link to a (relative) concept called 'welcome'.

{{{
&lt;gale:a href="tour" exec="#{tour#start,true};">...&lt;/gale:a>
}}}

This defines an adaptive link to a (relative) concept called 'tour' and when the link is
clicked the 'start' user model variable of this concept is set to 'true'.

{{{
&lt;gale:a href="welcome" adapt="false" class="good">Continue...&lt;/gale:a>
}}}

This defines a link to the 'welcome' concept that is always shown as a 'good' link.

=== Link Annotation ===

How a link should be adapted, based on the current state of the user model, is entirely
configurable. The css class can be changed based on an expression over the user model. The
default expression configured in GALE is:

{{{
(${#suitability}?(${#visited}>0?"neutral":"good"):"bad")
}}}

For suitable links it means that the class is 'good' for unvisited and 'neutral' for
visited links. An unsuitable link gets the class 'bad'. A different expression can be used
to decide on the css class using the {{{#link.classexpr}}} attribute. The value should be
a string that defines the expression. This expression is used in any content shown as part
of the concept containing the {{{#link.classexpr}}} attribute. Using css to annotate links
is part of [[../presentation|adaptive presentation]].

=== Link Hiding ===

The {{{#link.hide}}} attribute can be used to store an expression that determines if the
link should be hidden completely. Link hiding can be achieved through css by choosing the
same text color as normal text. However, the link will still be available. Using
{{{#link.hide}}} will cause the link itself to be removed, but the link text will remain
as normal text. The following piece of [[../gam|GAM]] code demonstrates its use:

{{{
http://gale.win.tue.nl/beer {
    #link.hide '!${#suitability}'
}
}}}

Using this GAM code, any link to a concept that appears in the content of the 'beer'
concept, will be hidden if the target concept is not 'suitable'. Similarly, link removal
can be achieved using {{{#link.remove}}}. When this Boolean attribute returns true, the
link will be removed completely, including the link text.

=== Icon Annotation ===

Links can be annotated using images. This is possible using the {{{#link.iconlist}}}
attribute. GALE expects this variable to yield a single expression or a list of
expressions. These expressions should in turn result in a URL (as string), pointing to the
image to use for annotations, or {{{null}}} if no image should be used. Example GAM code:

{{{
http://gale.win.tue.nl/beer {
    #link.iconlist '~
        if ("static-tree-view".equals(gale.currentView()))
            return (${#suitability}?(${#visited}>0?"pre:gale:/images/WhiteBall.gif":
              "pre:gale:/images/GreenBall.gif"):"pre:gale:/images/RedBall.gif");
        else
            return null;
    '
}
}}}

This example says that icons are only used in the 'static-tree-view' (the technical
name for the accordion menu) and it says that suitable links are prepended with a green
ball when unvisited and a white ball when visited and unsuitable links are prepended with
a red ball. Normally the icons are added after the link. Prepending the icon URL with
'pre:' will cause the icon to appear before the link.

=== &lt;gale:adapt-link> ===

In some cases the use of {{{&lt;gale:adapt-link>}}} is justified. It performs the same
type of adaptation, but does so on the parent tag. No attributes of
{{{&lt;gale:adapt-link>}}} are used. The second example on this page might be written like
this:

{{{
&lt;a href="tour" exec="#{tour#start,true};">&lt;gale:adapt-link />...&lt;/a>
}}}

Notice that the link anchor is not in the GALE namespace. Using the
{{{&lt;gale:adapt-link>}}} tag allows adaptation similar to that of link anchors, to
different tags. An example might be an image map:

{{{
&lt;span>
&lt;img usemap="#gale-architecture-image" src="images/gale-architecture.jpg" title="Gale Architecture" />
&lt;map name="gale-architecture-image">
&lt;area shape="rect" coords="170,35,285,73" href="system/concept-manager">&lt;gale:adapt-link />&lt;/area>
&lt;area shape="rect" coords="170,91,285,129" href="system/login-manager">&lt;gale:adapt-link />&lt;/area>
&lt;/map>
&lt;/span>
}}}

If this image map is combined with the previous code on link hiding, GALE will remove the
entire {{{&lt;area>}}} tag if the associated concept is 'unsuitable', thus creating an
adaptive image map.</gale:text>

</gale:repo>