<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">a module that includes the content from
another concept or file in the current XML document</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="long" type="creole">{{{
&lt;gale:object name="intro-fragment" />
}}}

The {{{&lt;gale:object>}}} tag allows the conditional inclusion of fragments. Using the
{{{name}}} attribute allows the inclusion of the content of relative concepts.
Alternatively the {{{data}}} attribute can be used to include a specific file.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole" expr="${processors#known}">The 'object' module
allows the content from another concept or file to be included. The
[[configuration|configuration]] links the 'object' module to the &lt;gale:object> tag. By
default the valid mime types are:
* "text/xhtml"
* "text/xml"
* "application/xml"
* "application/smil"</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">The {{{&lt;gale:object>}}} tag can be used to
include the content of another XML file. The 'data' attribute is used to specify the
location of the file, relative to the location of the current resource.
{{{
&lt;gale:object data="../header.xhtml" />
}}}

This will include the content of the header.xhtml file in the parent directory of the
resource containing the &lt;gale:object> tag. The content is treated is if it were part of
the original resource, and may contain any of the special GALE tags. The filename need not
be a constant. By using the [[attr-variable-module|]] you can assign a computed value to
any attribute of any XML element.

Instead of including another file, the {{{&lt;gale:object>}}} tag also allows the
inclusion of another concept. The content of the concept is retrieved as if through a
normal [[../locating-content|concept access]]. GALE will omit some layout related actions
on object concepts. This is done to ensure that only the actual concept content is
returned for the object. The content is inserted as is, because it has already been
adapted by GALE.

To include the content of another concept, the 'name' attribute is used. The name should
be an absolute or relative URI, and is resolved based on the current concept name.
{{{
&lt;gale:object name="intro-fragment" />
}}}

When a concept is included using {{{&lt;gale:object name="..." />}}}, this is a concept
access and thus causes UM updates. Because GALE traverses the DOM tree (of the page) in
depth first manner, the part that comes after processing this tag (and request) will be
adapted according to the updated UM state whereas the part before the tag was already
updated using the 'old' UM state and stays that way. It is thus possible to include the
same concept as an object on the same page multiple times and have it result in different
files being included for each occurrence.
</gale:text>

</gale:repo>