<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">using the GAM language or small snippets
of GAM code in other tools to create a domain model that includes adaptivity</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="long" type="creole">External tools can use (parts of) the GAM language to
add adaptivity to domain and course models created with the tools. An example can be found
in the [[../../research/gat|GRAPPLE Authoring Tools (GAT)]].</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">Any external authoring tool or converter could
deploy GAM files to GALE. In the [[../../research/grapple|]] project, graphical tools were
developed that aid the author in creating an adaptive application. These specific tools
create [[../../research/cam|.cam.xml]] files and present them to GALE upon deploy. A
special [[../../research/cam-compiler|CAM compiler]] interprets the file and the concepts
are stored in the GALE database. New tools should compile their own formats and present
GAM code to GALE.

The GRAPPLE authoring tools (GAT) use a parameterized version of GAM, much in the same way
as [[../../aha|AHA!]] used [[../../aha/templates|templates]] in its
[[../../aha/graph-author|Graph Author]]. Instead of explicitly identifying the concept in
the GAM code, a parameter is used that refers to the socket of a relation. Any number of
named sockets can be introduced to a relation type (Pedagogical Relation Type or PRT in
GAT), e.g., 'source' and 'target' in the case of a binary relation type. The type contains
a small fragment of GAM code that refers to the sockets:

{{{
%target% {
    #suitability:Boolean &amp;="${%source%#knowledge} > 0.7"
}
}}}

This code might define a prerequisite. It alters the {{{#suitability}}} expression of the
'target' concept(s). GAT allows any number of domain concepts to be stored in the target
socket. The suitability expression will be altered to include a part (or parts) that
checks whether the 'knowledge' of the source concept(s) is greater than 0.7.

Any GAM code is allowed in a PRT. It is possible to create entirely new concepts or domain
model relations based on the PRTs defined in the GAT course model. The following example
would create a new 'image' concept (for every concept in the 'self' socket of the unary
PRT) that shows the image based on a URL in the concept's 'image' property:

{{{
%self%/image {
    #resource "content:#image"
    #image '
        &lt;img>
        &lt;attr-variable xmlns="gale://gale.tue.nl/adaptation" name="src" expr="%self%?image" />
        &lt;/img>
    '
}
}}}
</gale:text>

</gale:repo>