<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">a generic adaptive hypermedia system
developed between 1996 and 2007 at the [[=http://www.tue.nl|TU/e]]</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="long" type="creole">The [[=http://aha.win.tue.nl|Adaptive Hypermedia
Architecture!]] was one of the first adaptive hypermedia systems that aimed at being
generic. Development started in 1996 by [[=http://wwwis.win.tue.nl/~~debra|Paul de Bra]]
at the [[=http://www.tue.nl|TU/e]]. The last official version of AHA! was 3.0, and was
released in 2007. Development on the next version continued and resulted in a new system
which was named [[gale|GALE]] in 2009.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole" expr="!${research/early-aha#known}">AHA! is an Open
Source adaptive hypermedia platform, capable of performing content and link adaptation in
(X)HTML and XML documents. Its development started in 1996. During 10 years of research
and development different new presentation, adaptation and user modeling methods and
techniques have been added, turning AHA! into a general-purpose adaptive hypermedia
platform. This section describes version 2 and 3 and is not a [[research/early-aha|history
on AHA!]].

Unlike other adaptive hypermedia systems, AHA! is not aimed at a single application area
and does not prescribe a single fixed presentation style. Creating applications, defining
the user models and the adaptive behavior are all done using graphical authoring tools.
End-users are presented with what looks like a normal website, and need not be aware of
the adaptation that goes on behind the scenes. Their browsing results in updates to a user
model that is stored either in an xml file or a mySQL database, and that is thus also (in
principle) available to other applications.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">An AHA! "installation" consists of a Java-based
webserver (like Tomcat), the AHA! software (servlets), and applications that consist of
(x)html pages, possibly other media objects, and conceptual information that defines how
AHA! needs to perform adaptation to the pages. The first figure below shows the global
architecture, and the second figure shows the different files or databases used by the
AHA! engine.

{{aha/images/global.gif|Image of global AHA! architecture}}

In the figure below we see that the AHA! engine uses three types of local information, and
potentially also pages that reside on other servers on the Web. The combined
[[aha/models|domain and adaptation model]] (DM/AM) represents a model of the conceptual
structure of the application, and the adaptation rules. This information is retrieved when
the end-user logs in. As the user is interacting with the application a user model (UM) is
used and constantly updated. The interaction involves (mostly) the retrieval of pages and
other application files (like images). DM/AM and UM are used to decide which application
file or "page" to retrieve upon a request from the user (and which objects to
conditionally include in that page). The request may also result in files being retrieved
from other webservers.

{{aha/images/engine.gif|Image of AHA! engine}}

What the global architecture shows is that the way in which AHA! can perform adaptation is
limited mostly by the HTTP request-response paradigm. Each request invokes a fixed
procedure or sequence of steps the engine performs in order to return an adapted
page.</gale:text>

</gale:repo>