<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">how the work described in this thesis
answers the [[questions|research questions]] and its impact</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">== Discussion and Impact</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;long" type="creole"></gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">//Adaptive hypermedia// has great potential. There
seems to be no end to the amount of information available on the World Wide Web today.
When authors, publishing this huge amount, would have the ability to write things
differently or write different things, based on their knowledge of the reader, would they
use that power? One can never answer that question without having realized the technical
context to support it.

Many adaptive hypermedia systems have been created. However, the added complexity of
authoring adaptive hypermedia and the limited functionality and performance issues of
adaptive hypermedia systems have limited the amount of material produced. This thesis,
and accompanying prototype [[gale|GALE]], is based on 15 years of experience of authors
writing adaptive hypermedia and engineers developing systems to support them. It answers
the [[questions]] raised in the introduction.

GALE is a 'generic' AHS. It can perform most adaptation using rules that govern the
[[gale/adaptation-model|adaptive behavior]]. It is easily
[[gale/system/extending|extended]] to add new functionality. GALE is 'usable' in the sense
that authoring adaptive behavior is not needlessly complex. Authoring can be complex,
because adaptive behavior can be complex. However, GALE allows authors to
[[gale/gam/relation|inherit]] adaptive behavior defined elsewhere. Not only can the
content be distributed over the Internet, the domain and adaptation model can be
distributed as well, allowing for 'open model adaptation'.

[[performance|Performance]] matters. This is not something that should be easily
disregarded by engineers of adaptive hypermedia systems. Readers tend to avoid slow web
sites. The acceptance of adaptive sites may be hampered by excessive latency caused by
slow adaptation engines. Furthermore, the Internet allows potentially many concurrent
readers. Poor performance will likely get worse when more people are reading. GALE has
great performance, as you can experience from reading this thesis on a server that not 
only simultaneously delivers several adaptive applications to many different users but
also server the Information Systems Group's website, Learning Management System and other
applications.

The existence of a flexible generic adaptive hypermedia system that performs well offers a
technological basis for further research into the nature and usefulness of adaptive 
hypermedia. Further improvements to performance and acceptance can be realized in the
[[future-work|future]].</gale:text>

</gale:repo>