<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">a generic adaptive hypermedia system
developed at the [[=http://www.tue.nl|TU/e]]</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="long" type="creole">The Generic Adaptation Language and Engine (GALE) is
the successor of [[aha|AHA!]]. GALE was developed at the [[=http://www.tue.nl|TU/e]] in
the context of the [[research/grapple|GRAPPLE]] research project. It is being used by
several universities and companies. Adaptive course material is served by GALE and, as
part of courses on adaptive hypermedia, students are required to create their own adaptive
applications using GALE.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole" expr="!${research#known}">The Generic Adaptation
Language and Engine (GALE) is the result of the ongoing research effort to create a
generic adaptive hypermedia system. It allows a wide range of adaptive techniques
described in [[research|adaptive hypermedia research]].</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">Traditional Web servers provide static content to
Web clients. The server stores [[=http://www.w3.org/TR/html4/|HTML]] files written by an
author and makes them available through the
[[=http://www.w3.org/Protocols/rfc2616/rfc2616.html|HTTP]] protocol. The Web client,
usually a browser, receives the file and renders the content as a page on the screen.

GALE acts like a traditional Web server in that it provides mostly (X)HTML content to Web
clients using the HTTP protocol. The content does not necessarily need to be stored on the
GALE server (allowing GALE to adapt the full open corpus of the Web). GALE differs in that
it uses actions taken by the user, like requesting a specific topic, to update a profile.
This profile can have a great influence on the actual (X)HTML content sent to the Web
client. GALE can detect links to topics that might be too difficult or might just be
uninteresting for the user that made the request. Blocks of hypermedia can be shown or
hidden based on the user profile. Almost any [[research/taxonomy|adaptive technique]] can
be realised using GALE, which makes it a //generic// platform for adaptive hypermedia.

To perform adaptation, GALE requires input that defines the adaptive behavior. Several
[[gale/models-languages|models and languages]] can be used to provide this input. Though
these can be written using a simple text editor, some authors might prefer tools developed
in the [[research/grapple|GRAPPLE]] project.

Authoring an adaptive application often involves writing [[gale/adaptation|content]] (or
reusing already written content). Though adaptive content selection and adaptive
presentation are possible without changing the content in any way, GALE provides powerful
tools to enhance the content itself and make it adaptive.

GALE is a Java servlet-based adaptive hypermedia system. It can be installed on existing
web servers like [[=http://tomcat.apache.org|Tomcat]] or
[[=http://www.mortbay.org|Jetty]]. A [[gale/system|modular architecture]] is used to split
functionality into logical components. The components are separated to the extent that
they could run on different physical machines and still work as a whole. This allows great
[[gale/system/extending|customization]] of any part of GALE, without affecting the other
components.</gale:text>

</gale:repo>