<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo
    xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">
    <gale:text tag="default" type="creole">
        When using this application you will be presented with several questions and scenarios regarding your personal and professional life. After answering all questions, you will get a personalized advice on how to deal with the symptoms of burnout you might show. Eventually, you can reflect on your own behavior and ideally change that behavior if necessary.
    </gale:text>

   <!-- Start Card -->
   <div class="row page" id="page-1">
           <div class="card teal darken-2">
             <div class="card-content white-text">
               <span class="card-title">Adaptive Questions</span>
               <p>First you will be presented with one of the questions. This can be either a textual question, or an image. Upon answering the question, you will be redirected to a different question. The order of questions you will see is based on the answers you provide.</p>
             </div>
         </div>
   </div>
   <!-- End card -->

   <!-- Start Card -->
   <div class="row page" id="page-2">
           <div class="card teal darken-2">
             <div class="card-content white-text">
               <span class="card-title">Question Styles</span>
               <p>Questions can be displayed textually or in image-form. If you would like to switch the way questions are displayed, you can click the 'Show as image' or 'Show as text' buttons under the question.</p>
             </div>
         </div>
   </div>
   <!-- End card -->

   <!-- Start Card -->
   <div class="row page" id="page-3">
           <div class="card teal darken-2">
             <div class="card-content white-text">
               <span class="card-title">Jokes</span>
               <p>Throughout the questionaire, a red badge will appear at the bottom right of your screen. This badge can be clicked to display a joke to help you stick your attention to the application.</p>
             </div>
         </div>
   </div>
   <!-- End card -->

   <!-- Start Card -->
   <div class="row page" id="page-4">
           <div class="card teal darken-2">
             <div class="card-content white-text">
               <span class="card-title">Results</span>
               <p>After you completed all your questions, you will be presented with an overview of stressors that could be causing a burnout. Useful tips will be given to help you stay stress-free and handle work-related problems in your life.</p>
             </div>
         </div>
   </div>
   <!-- End card -->
    <div class="col s12 m7 l6 pagination">
        <div id="pagination-short"></div>
    </div>

   <gale:text tag="default" type="creole">
       If you know how to use this system, you can continue to the question pages.
   </gale:text>
    <div class="waves-effect waves-light btn btn-small"><i class="material-icons right">keyboard_arrow_right</i>
    <gale:text tag="default" type="creole">
         [[question|To questions]]
    </gale:text>
    </div>
</gale:repo>
