<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">giving a gentle introduction to the
material in the thesis and its context</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="long" type="creole">The technology described in this thesis will allow an
author to create //adaptive hypermedia//, a text that will depend on the reader's
knowledge, interest, goals, etc. Several considerations have played an important role in
the design of the developed languages, models and systems:
* reading an adaptive hypertext should not be slower than reading a traditional hypertext,
* authors should be able to express any adaptivity based on the user,
* the full complexity of adaptive behavior should be hidden from authors that don't need
  to see or change it,
* setting up the required adaptive hypermedia system should be easy.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">Authors have used written text for centuries to
convey ideas. They were constrained by the linear nature of books, papers, and the like.
Hypertext has empowered authors, in that it allows interlinking fragments and pages of
text and thus creating a document that is radically different from a linear text. Going 
from linear text to hypertext requires a change in mindset for both authors and readers. 
Only when authors come to convey ideas using this newfound power and when readers learn to
cope with this new navigational freedom, will hypertext reach its full potential.

Though the idea of hypertext dates back to the 1940's 
[[references?tags=Bush45|[Bush45~]]], it was not until the technological context was 
available that authors started to use it en masse. However, the same technological context 
can be used to empower authors even further. Conveying ideas is still the driving force 
behind any authoring, linear text and hypertext. Taking your readers into account while 
writing, is something every author should do. The technology described in this thesis will 
allow an author to create //adaptive hypermedia//, a text that will depend on the reader's 
knowledge, interest, goals, etc.

When World Wide Web was first introduced it was intended as a means for sharing
information. It uses information pages and links, and is therefore a form of hypermedia.
Nowadays the Web is being used as a common user interface platform for all different kinds
of applications, from communication (through discussion forums), shopping, banking and
other global types of services down to controlling your heating, lighting and other types
of devices in the home, and using interface devices ranging from mobile phones to huge
computer monitors and wall-size displays. This thesis does not deal with the possibilities
for adaptive technology in all these aspects of the Web, but concentrates on the Web as
the hypermedia platform it is mainly used for: we look at applications in which users
interact with information (pages), like in on-line courses, news-services, museum sites,
(shopping) catalogs, encyclopedia, etc. We look at how these applications can adapt
themselves to their individual users or user groups, through the interaction of the users
with the applications.

The main focus of the work described here was to create the technological context
necessary to support authors in creating these //adaptive hypermedia// applications. As 
such, we call the development author-driven. Several considerations have played an 
important role in the design of the developed languages, models and systems:
* reading (accessing) an adaptive hypertext should not be slower than reading a 
  traditional hypertext,
* authors should be able to express any adaptivity based on the user,
* the full complexity of adaptive behavior should be hidden from authors who don't need
  to see or change it,
* setting up the required adaptive hypermedia system should be easy.

Designing a system that takes these considerations into account has led to several
[[questions]].</gale:text>

</gale:repo>