<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">the papers, book chapters, and magazine
articles that form the basis of this thesis</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">== Literature that this thesis is based on</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default;long" type="creole">Various research papers, book chapters and
magazine articles have already been published about the material discussed in this thesis.
This section contains a brief 'glossary' of this published work and provides some pointers
to their relation to the thesis.</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">
**A Fully Generic Approach for Realizing the Adaptive Web**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
De Bra, P., Smits, D. (2012)<br/>
Sofsem 2012 conference, Czech Republic, January 22-26, 2012. (pp. 64-76) Springer LNCS.
</span>

Describing the GALE [[gale/system|architecture]], the [[gale/gam|GAM]] language and some
of GALE's advanced [[gale/system/caching|caching features]].
<hr/>

**GRAPPLE: Learning Management Systems meet Adaptive Learning Environments**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
De Bra, P., Smits, D., van der Sluijs, K., Cristea, A.I., Foss, J., Glahn, C., Steiner, C. (2012 to appear)<br/>
Chapter 6, In: Intelligent and Adaptive Educational-Learning Systems: Achievements and Trends, Smart Innovation, Systems and Technologies, KES-Springer Verlang Book Series, 2012
</span>

A complete overview of what has been achieved in the [[research/grapple|GRAPPLE project]].
<hr/>

**Bridging navigation, search and adaptation: adaptive hypermedia models evolution**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
Knutov, E., Bra, P. de, Smits, D., Pechenizkiy, M. (2011)<br/>
Proceedings of the 7th International Conference on Web Information Systems and Technologies (WEBIST 2011, Noordwijkerhout, The Netherlands, May 6-9, 2011)
</span>

Providing one of the ideas mentioned as [[future-work|future work]].
<hr/>

**GALE: a highly extensible adaptive hypermedia engine**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
Smits, D., De Bra, P. (2011)<br/>
Proceedings of the 22nd ACM Conference on Hypertext and Hypermedia (Eindhoven, The Netherlands, June 6-9, 2011)
</span>

The [[gale/system|GALE architecture]] and [[gale/modifying-resource|authoring]].
<hr/>

**GRAPPLE: Personalization and adaptation in learning management systems**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
De Bra, P., Smits, D., Sluijs, K.A.M. van der, Cristea, A.I., Hendrix, M. (2010)<br/>
Proceedings of World Conference on Educational Multimedia, Hypermedia and Telecommunications 2010
</span>

Authoring for GALE using the [[research/gat|GRAPPLE Authoring Tools (GAT)]].
<hr/>

**Making today's Learning Management Systems adaptive**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
Oneto, L., Abel, F., Herder, E., Smits, S. (2009)<br/>
Learning Management Systems meet Adaptive Learning Environments, Workshop at European Conference on Technology Enhanced Learning (ECTEL)
</span>

Integrating GALE in LMSs in the [[research/grapple|GRAPPLE]] project using
[[research/gumf|GUMF]].
<hr/>

**Unifying adaptive learning environments : authoring styles in the GRAPPLE project**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
De Bra, P., Smits, D., Knutov, E., Ploum, E., Sluijs, K.A.M. van der (2009)<br/>
Adjunct Proceedings First International Conference on User Modeling, Adaptation, and Personalization (UMAP 2009, Trento, Italy, June 22-26, 2009)
</span>

Different methods of authoring adaptive content.
<hr/>

**LAG 2.0: Refining a reusable adaptation language and improving on its authoring**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
Cristea, A.I., Smits, D., Bevan, J.D., Hendrix, M. (2009)<br/>
Learning in the synergy of multiple disciplines: 4th european conference on technology enhanced learning (EC-TEL 2009 Nice, France, September 29-October 2, 2009)
</span>

Strategy based approach to adaptation arguing that simple adaptation rules like those
found in AHA! may not be enough.
<hr/>

**GRAPPLE: Integrating adaptive learning into learning management systems**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
De Bra, P., Pechenizkiy, M., Sluijs, K.A.M. van der, Smits, D. (2008)<br/>
Proceedings of World Conference on Educational Multimedia, Hypermedia and Telecommunications 2008
</span>

Early ideas on GRAPPLE, taking functions in the [[aha/graph-author|]] and using them in
[[research/gat|GAT]].
<hr/>

**Adaptivity in GRAPPLE: Adaptation in any way you like (Poster)**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
De Bra, P., Smits, D., Pechenizkiy, M., Vasilyeva, E. (2008)
Proceedings of the World Conference on E-Learning in Corporate, Government, Healthcare and Higher Education (E-Learn 2008, Las Vegas NV, USA, November 17-21, 2008)
</span>

Showing the intermediate version of AHA! (version 4) that resulted from
[[research/als|ALS]] and was further developed within [[research/grapple|GRAPPLE]].
<hr/>

**Defining adaptation in a generic multi layer model: CAM: The GRAPPLE Conceptual Adaptation Model**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
Hendrix, M., De Bra, P., Pechenizkiy, M., Smits, D., Cristea, A.I. (2008)
Third European Conference on Technology Enhanced Learning (EC-TEL 2008, Maastricht, September 18-19, 2008, Proceedings)
</span>

Early ideas on the [[research/cam|Conceptual Adaptation Model]].
<hr/>

**Authoring and management tools for adaptive educational hypermedia systems: the AHA! case study**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
De Bra, P., Stash, N., Smits, D., Romero, C., Ventura, S. (2007)
Evolution of Teaching and Learning Paradigms in Intelligent Environment (pp. 285-308) Berlin: Springer
</span>

Detailing the various tools available to [[aha/authoring|author]] applications in AHA!,
including the [[aha/concept-editor|]] and [[aha/graph-author|]].
<hr/>

**Towards a generic adaptive hypermedia platform: a conversion case study**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
Cristea, A.I., Smits, D., De Bra, P. (2007)
Journal of Digital Information, 8(3)
</span>

Converting from MOT and LAG to AHA!; how high level adaptation strategies can be compiled
to low level adaptation rules.
<hr/>

**Specification, authoring and prototyping of personalised workplace learning solutions**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
Dolog, P., Kravcik, M., Cristea, A.I., Burgos, D., De Bra, P., Ceri, S., Devedzic, V., Houben, G.J.P.M., Libbrecht, P., Matera, M., Melis, E., Nejdl, W., Specht, M., Stewart, C., Smits, D., Stash, N., Tattersall, C. (2007)
International Journal of Learning Technology, 3(3) (pp. 286-308)
</span>

Reviewing models and languages available to describe a problem domain and adaptation.
<hr/>

**The design of AHA!**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
De Bra, P., Smits, D., Stash, N. (2006)
Proceedings of the 17th ACM Conference on Hypertext and Hypermedia (HT'06, Odense, Denmark, August 22-25, 2006)
</span>

Overview of AHA!'s [[aha/system|architecture]]. The world's first
[[=http://aha.win.tue.nl/ahadesign|adaptive paper]].
<hr/>

**Creating and delivering adaptive courses with AHA!**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
De Bra, P., Smits, D., Stash, N. (2006)
Proceedings 1st European Conference on Technology Enhanced Learning (EC-TEL 2006, Crete, Greece, October 1-4, 2006)
</span>

Explaining the [[aha/models|domain model]] used in [[aha|AHA!]].
<hr/>

**Writing MOT, reading AHA!: converting between an authoring and a delivery system for adaptive educational hypermedia**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
Cristea, A.I., Smits, D., De Bra, P. (2005)
Proceedings Third International Workshop on Authoring of Adaptive and Adaptable Educational Hypermedia (A3EH; in conjunction with AIED'05, Amsterdam, The Netherlands, July 18-22, 2005)
</span>

Experience with compiling/translating adaptive strategies to adaptive "assembly" rules.
Lead to ideas to improve the authoring power in AHA! and later GALE.
<hr/>

**Creating adaptive textbooks with AHA!**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
De Bra, P., Stash, N., Smits, D. (2004)
Proceedings of the World Conference on E-Learning in Corporate, Government, Healthcare and Higher Education (E-Learn 2004, Washington DC, USA, November 1-5, 2004)
</span>

<hr/>

**Creating adaptive applications with AHA! (Tutorial for AHA! version 3.0)**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
De Bra, P., Stash, N., Smits, D. (2004)
AH 2004: Tutorials (Computer Science Reports, Vol. 04-20, pp. 1-29) Eindhoven: Technische Universiteit Eindhoven
</span>

<hr/>

**Creating adaptive textbooks with AHA! (roundtable)**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
De Bra, P., Stash, N., Smits, D., Smits, D. (2004)
Proceedings of World Conference on E-Learning in Corporate, Government, Healthcare, and Higher Education 2004
</span>

<hr/>

**AHA! The adaptive hypermedia architecture**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
De Bra, P., Aerts, A., Berden, B., Lange, B. de, Rousseau, B.J.P., Santic, T., Smits, D., Stash, N. (2003)
Proceedings of the 14th ACM Conference on Hypertext and Hypermedia (HT 2003, Nottingham, UK, August 26-30, 2003)
</span>

<hr/>

**AHA! meets AHAM**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
De Bra, P., Aerts, A., Smits, D., Stash, N. (2002)
Adaptive Hypermedia and Adaptive Web-Based Systems (Proceedings AH 2002, Malaga, Spain, May 29-31, 2002)
</span>

<hr/>

**AHA! Version 2.0, More adaptation flexibility for authors**\\
<span style="font-size:small">
De Bra, P., Aerts, A., Smits, D., Stash, N. (2002)
Proceedings of the World Conference on E-Learning in Corporate, Government, Healthcare and Higher Education (E-Learn 2002, Montreal, Canada, October 15-19, 2002)
</span>

</gale:text>

</gale:repo>