<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gale:repo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
xmlns:gale="http://gale.tue.nl/adaptation">

<gale:text tag="short" flat="true" type="creole">hypermedia that is adapted to suit the
needs of individual users based on a profile that can change over time</gale:text>

<gale:text tag="default" type="creole">The fields of //intelligent tutoring systems// and
//hypermedia// came together when the Web evolved to the point where it became feasible to
add enough functionality to the Web server back-end. The award-winning ELM-ART adaptive
Lisp course [[references?tags=Brus96|[Brus96~]]] not only paved the way for later
developments but also set a standard for //adaptive link annotations// by employing a
"traffic light metaphor" of using green and red balls (and some intermediate colors like
white and yellow) to indicate the "status" of links to course topics or pages. This
metaphor was inherited by many later systems and can still be seen in some GALE
applications as well.

When Brusilovsky created Interbook [[references?tags=Brus98|[Brus98~]]] he aimed at
creating a platform that could be used for many courses (instead of the single Lisp course
offered by ELM-ART). He used Microsoft Word as the authoring platform. An author would
essentially write a textbook in Word. Fragments (paragraphs or sections) of text would be
associated with some //outcome concepts// by means of a structured comment, and concepts
would be indicated as being a //prerequisite for// other concepts, also by means of a
comment. Converting a textbook (written in Word) into an adaptive on-line course was
reduced to little more than a press of a button.

Adaptation is always based on information the system has about its user. Therefore //user
modeling// is a key component in every adaptive system. Typically user modeling is based
on rules that "translate" user actions into user information. Reading a course page means
that you learn about a concept. That knowledge can be confirmed through a test. That
knowledge is also used to check whether you satisfy //prerequisites// for studying other
concepts. Knowledge levels of small concepts also "add up" to knowledge about chapters and
whole courses. This description may give the false impression that an adaptive system
really "knows" what goes on in the user's mind, with absolute certainty. There is however
an alternative approach to user modeling, using Bayesian networks. This approach is taken
by KBS-Hyperbook [[references?tags=Henze00|[Henze00~]]] for instance. User actions change
the "belief" of the system that the user has certain knowledge. It is easier to deal with
positive and negative "evidence" of the user's knowledge (or interest or any other type of
information) in Bayesian networks than in systems that just use (event-condition-action)
rules to update knowledge levels.

[[research/early-aha|Early versions of AHA!]] (the Adaptive Hypermedia Architecture)
associated pages with concepts and for each concept the system could track the user's
knowledge. A concept could require prior knowledge and could, when accessed, generate
knowledge. [[aha|Recent versions]] [[references?tags=DeBra03;DeBra06|[DeBra03, DeBra06~]]]
allow an author to define arbitrary //adaptation rules// (in fact //user model update
rules//) and can thus support any model or interpretation of the information stored about
users. Also, unlike Interbook's use of Microsoft Word for authoring, applications in all
versions of AHA! are authored in HTML, and of course also delivered as HTML. This means
that authors familiar with creating HTML can give an AHA! application any look and feel
they desire. AHA! can for instance completely mimic the behavior and presentation of
Interbook [[references?tags=DeBra03-2|[DeBra03-2~]]].

In order to be able to manage the complexity of having //arbitrary adaptation rules// and
//arbitrary presentation// AHA! had to separate the authoring of the adaptation from the
authoring of the content and presentation. Defining complex adaptation rules requires very
different skills from writing the content of a course. We <gale:if
expr="${gale/models-languages#known-all}"> <gale:then>have seen</gale:then><gale:else>will
see</gale:else></gale:if> this in [[gale|GALE]] as well. Not every type of web-based
system that includes adaptivity will be easy to create in GALE, as the
[[research/related-work|related work]] shows. But research on
[[research/taxonomy|adaptation techniques]] has given a good insight into what most
systems have in common.</gale:text>

</gale:repo>